<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A plea for the vse of gospell ordinances: against the practice and opinions of certain men of these times. Unto which is added by way of an illustrious instance; a vindication of the ordinance of baptisme: against Mr. Dels booke, entituled The doctrine of baptismes. Wherein it's proved that the ordinance of baptism is of gospel institution, and by divine appointment, to continue of use in the Church, to the end of the world. / By Hen: Laurence Esq;.</title>
            <author>Lawrence, Henry, 1600-1664.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 162 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 47 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88811</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L668</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E654_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205905</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865135</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865135</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117372</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88811)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117372)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 100:E654[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A plea for the vse of gospell ordinances: against the practice and opinions of certain men of these times. Unto which is added by way of an illustrious instance; a vindication of the ordinance of baptisme: against Mr. Dels booke, entituled The doctrine of baptismes. Wherein it's proved that the ordinance of baptism is of gospel institution, and by divine appointment, to continue of use in the Church, to the end of the world. / By Hen: Laurence Esq;.</title>
                  <author>Lawrence, Henry, 1600-1664.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 80, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by M.S. for Livewell Chapman, at the Crown in Popes-head Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: Dell, William, d. 1664  Baptismōn didachē.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: The "2" in the imprint date is crossed out and date altered to 1651; "Febr. 5.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dell, William, d. 1664. --  Baptismōn didachē.</term>
               <term>Baptism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117372:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A PLEA for the Vſe of Goſpell Ordinances: Againſt the Practice And Opinions of certain men of theſe times. Unto which is added By way of an illuſtrious Inſtance; <hi>A Vindication of the Ordinance of BAPTISME:</hi> AGAINST M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Dels Booke, ENTITULED <hi>The Doctrine of Baptiſmes.</hi> Wherein it's proved That the Ordinance of <hi>Baptiſm</hi> is of Goſpel In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, and by Divine appointment, to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue of uſe in the Church, to the end of the World.</p>
            <p>By HEN: LAURENCE <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
            </p>
            <q>Beware leaſt any man ſpoyle you through Philoſophy, and vain deceit, after the tradition of men, after the Rudiments of the world, and not after Chriſt. <bibl>
                  <hi>Col. 2.8.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> printed by <hi>M. S.</hi> for <hi>Livewell Chapman,</hi> at the Crown in Popeſ-head Alley. 1652.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:117372:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:117372:2"/>
            <head>TO My moſt Deare, and moſt Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured Mother, the LADY LAWRENCE:</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt Honoured Mother,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>EE heare much of late of certain civil Hereticks, they call the <hi>LEVELLERS;</hi> Men, who by pretending <hi>Salus Populi,</hi> and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good, would render their owne ſhare in the World, better then it is: And finding (as their Lots are caſt) commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity more advantageous to them, then proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, would take away all thoſe troubleſome bounds, and metes, which Laws or Cuſtomes
<pb facs="tcp:117372:3"/>
have eſtabliſhed upon particular rights, that all things might be reduced to their Primitive (as they pretend) and Originall Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
            <p>I deſigne not the proceſſe of theſe Men at this time, how great ſoever their crime may be, and great enough certainly it will be judged, if this Charge be true: But the Charge that this Diſcourſe intends, is againſt another, and more audacious kind of <hi>Levellers,</hi> ſpirituall <hi>Levellers,</hi> men that would levell God; and as it was the vanity and ambition of <hi>Adam,</hi> to make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe like God, ſo it is the preſumption, and pride of theſe men, to make God like them. We have formerly had to doe with ſome, who would bring the Juſtice of God, to the modell and ſcantling of their juſtice, which hath been the occaſion of that great controverſie with the <hi>Pelagians,</hi> and their followers the <hi>Arminians.</hi> And now we are importun'd by a Generation of men, who would ſubject the wiſedome of God to the modell and ſcantling of their wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, would give lawes to God, for the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and Oeconomy of his owne houſe, and judge all at an undue and under rate,
<pb facs="tcp:117372:3"/>
that lye not levell with their either reaſon, or fancy. And becauſe (ſelfe-love making up in us all defects) men are uſually reaſonably well ſatisfied with their own wiſdomes, howſoever others are; and that as the Scripture ſayes, <hi>Vaine Man would be wiſe, though Man bee as a wild Aſſes Colt;</hi> Hence it is, that men who have not lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſufficiently, that <hi>the fooliſhneſſe of God is wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer then men,</hi> and therfore <hi>if any man would be wiſe he muſt become a foole that he may be wiſe;</hi> men that have not been taught this of God, are vying ſtil with God for wiſedome, and are extreamely ſcandalized at his method of ſaving men by the <hi>fooliſh, and baſe, and weake, and deſpiſed meanes of Preaching,</hi> with all other Ordinances and Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions.</p>
            <p>Our Saviour and Maſter taught us better by his owne example, when conſidering of the reaſon why God had <hi>hid the great things of the Goſpell, from the wiſe and learned men of the World, and revealed them to Babes:</hi> He reſolved it eaſily into the good pleaſure of God; <hi>Even ſo Father, for ſo it pleaſed thee.</hi> But theſe will rather diſpute it out with God and Men, then they will ſuffer ſuch a blemiſh to their wiſedome, as the ayde
<pb facs="tcp:117372:4"/>
and aſſiſtance that <hi>theſe fooliſh, and weake, and baſe deſpiſed things,</hi> (as the Scripture cals them) brings with them. And yet becauſe it is hard to make an open Warre againſt God, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent and evident truths, held forth in his Word, they imploy all the pittance of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome they have, to this great worke of <hi>Level<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,</hi> either in wholly taking away the uſe of the Scriptures, to themſelves and others of their elevation, or by ſo mincing and altering them by their liberty of allegorizing (Which you muſt beleeve although it be nonſence to be <hi>the Myſtery of the Hiſtory,</hi> as they call it) as they make them ſpeake what they judge in wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome they ſhould, ſince of themſelves and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally they are farre from ſpeaking what they would.</p>
            <p>But I ſhall trouble you no farther (moſt Honoured Mother) with prefacing, having given you a ſhort account who they are, and what it is that this diſcourſe pretends againſt, as the title tels you what it pretends to.</p>
            <p>I am not (I thanke God) ſo vaine as to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that this Eſſay ſhould convert this kind of men, eſpecially ſuch as are higheſt flowne, and
<pb facs="tcp:117372:4"/>
who having beene accuſtomed to defie rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Scripture, doe not uſe to bee ſatisfied when they are anſwered. But I am not without hopes (through the grace of God) but that it may be of uſe to ſome, truly godly (for theſe temptations are fitted to perſons and places of light) who <hi>have not known the depths of Sathan,</hi> nor are yet effectually inſnared by theſe ſtratagems and wiles of the Devill. And I am aſſured, it will be accepted by you (my Deare Mother) to whom I preſent it, not only upon that juſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count that you commanded it (and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of Parents to their Children are of the higheſt Prerogative:) But becauſe it will be ſatisfaction to you to ſee the Aſſerting and Vindicating of thoſe things indeavored, which have ſo much of truth, and God in them; and in a time, when the profeſſion and practice of them is expos'd not onely to the inſultings of men openly and profeſſedly prophane, but which is leſſe ſufferable, and more abominable, to the ſcorne and contempt of ſuch as would be eſteemed Saints of the higheſt elevation. But <hi>Wiſedome is juſtified of her Children,</hi> whoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition is very eaſily ſupportable with this aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,
<pb facs="tcp:117372:5"/>
               <hi>That as Chriſt was in the World, ſo are they in the World;</hi> and if <hi>Their life be hid with Chriſt in God, when Chriſt who is their life, ſhall appeare, they ſhall appeare with him in glory:</hi> I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Moſt Honoured Mother,</salute>
               <signed>Your moſt obedient Sonne, and Moſt Humble Servant, <hi>Henry Lawrence.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:117372:5"/>
            <head>A VINDICATION OF THE SCRIPTURES, And Chriſtian Ordinances.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>OTHING ſeems more to ſpeak the miſery of theſe evil and calamitous times in which we live, then the extreame debordment of extravagant Opinions in matters of Religion, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe of which tend not onely directly to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermining of Holineſſe, and Chriſtian Religion (which by the grace of God hath been long acknowledged and profeſſed in this Kingdome) but to the ſubverſion alſo, and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of civill ſociety, and communion with men as men.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:117372:6"/>The riſe of which exorbitancy (ſo far as my ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation leads me) is laid. Firſt in a ſlighting of the Ordinances of worſhip, as things leſſe profitable and uſefull and more befitting Children then grown men, and then (according to the nature of errour which is eaſily multiplying and increaſing, for one abſurdity granted a hundred will follow and grow out of it) in a reprobating and utter caſting of thoſe Ordinances as things hurtfull and deſtructive to the nature of of Saintſhip, and altogether unproper and unmeet for that ſtate of growth and perfection which they pretend to have attained unto.</p>
            <p>This wile of the Devill is not by all good men ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily and at the firſt obſerved, not doe they conſider that by a ſhew of rationall and ſpirituall pretences, he deprives them at laſt of all the Ordinances and Inſtitutions of God, that his inſpirations and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations may be in ſtead of them, and he at laſt may be all in all unto them.</p>
            <p>For I beſeech you, what elſe is the effect of thoſe methods in theſe men in whom he hath gained moſt upon this way, but a forme of unſound words, by which evill communication they corrups good man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; ſtuffing their Preachings and Writings with an uncouth and moſt unſavory gibberiſh, or jergon language, which the Scriptures owne not, which ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall and truely ſpirituall men underſtand not, till at laſt growing bolder in the vanities of their minds and expreſſions, they come to this to which ſome of them are come to make themſelves Chriſt and God, and to ſtile themſelves the Lord of Hoſts. Blaſphemies unheard of in other ages, and ſuch as are capable of aſtoniſhing the moſt debauch't and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:117372:6"/>
prophane ſpirits, and ſuch as tend not onely to the utter ſubverſion of all Religion, but as a neceſſary conſequence of that, to the deſtruction and diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all bands of civill government.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding the horrour of theſe things, yet I muſt profeſſe, when I thinke ſeriouſly of them I cannot but reſt ſatisfied in the wiſedome and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God to his; who by letting them ſee the miſerable conſequences and effects of opinions ſo depraved as the caſting aſide of all Ordinances of worſhip, and yet of that ſeeming holineſſe and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritualneſſe as the pretence of a more immediate and ſpirituall converſe with God is, are bounded and kept in order by theſe exorbitancies, and taught that which the Scripture teacheth frequently; that <hi>The weakneſſe of God is ſtronger then men, and the fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God is wiſer then men;</hi> and therefore if any will be wiſe (for all theſe vanities ariſe from no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but from a carnall and vaine Philoſophating a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſpirituall things) <hi>he muſt become a foole that hee may be wiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now as to be inſtrumentall, to <hi>turne ſinners and ſuch as erre from the truth, from the errour of their ways,</hi> is a thing of the greateſt concernment, and highly acceptable to God, ſo is it no way of more conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, then in ſuch errings and miſtakings as are about the fundamentals of Religion and Worſhip, and which are ſo fertile of ill, as having gained once a prevalency and authority, there is no ſtoppe or bounds to any thing, which a vaine and carnall heart, deluded and imboldened by the Devill, ſhall broach to the World for good Doctrine.</p>
            <p>That which immediately debauches the ſpirit of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:117372:7"/>
men this way, is (as I ſaid) a ſlighting and underva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luing of the Ordinances of worſhip, and holy Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions; and after that, a deſpiſing and abhorring of them as things carnall and unbecomming a ſpirituall and raiſed ſtate: But that which is yet a deeper, and more bottome root of this untoward production: is,</p>
            <p>Secondly, Low and meane thoughts of the holy Scriptures, the Word of God; or which is as bad, and ariſes from the ſame root of pride and vanity, ſuch a bold and ridiculous allegorizing of them, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a colour of going farre enough from the Letter, and underſtanding the myſtery of them, as they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trude upon you all the vaine reaſonings of a carnall heart, and that (as the Preachings and Writings of theſe times will abundantly witneſſe) with ſuch folly and madneſſe, as that after that rate a man may not deſpaire to ſee the <hi>Turkiſh Alcoran</hi> brought out of the New Teſtament; or (if there be any greater) the greateſt abſurdities and follies that ever entered into the heart of any ignorant or carnall man, ſince the World ſtood.</p>
            <p>He therefore that would indeavour the recovery of theſe men, or prevent the fallings and diſorders of others, in theſe matters of greateſt concernment, had need ſpeake ſomething to ſuch errings as are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Scriptures. And,</p>
            <p>Firſt, Not to ſpeake (if there bee any ſuch) of thoſe that queſtion the Divine Authority of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as if it had not God for its Author, and Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall; that which I ſhall ſpeake ſomething to, is that Opinion which ſeemes to be received amongſt ſome, as if it were a ſtraitning to the ſpirit of God,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:117372:7"/>
and indignity offered to it, to bring ſpirituall reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations to the touch-ſtone and <hi>Examen</hi> of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. On the other ſide, to me, the Scripture ſeems amongſt others, to have t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o excellent ends for our advantage; the one, as other Ordinances of God, to be a <hi>Medium</hi> of his owne ſetting up, and which he delights to uſe, for the conveying of himſelfe to our ſpirits, in inlightening and ſanctifying us, and making us partakers of the Divine nature. The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to be a certaine and fixt Standard, to which we may bring any thing that is broacht, under the name of ſpirituall truth; and may thereby (as the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſayes) <hi>Try the ſpirits whether they be of God;</hi> may know the voyce of God from the voyce of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, and the voyce of the holy ſpirit and good An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, from that of Satan, even when he transformes himſelfe into an Angel of light. Nor is this any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignity offered to the ſpirit of God, as is before pretended, ſince he is confined to no Rule, but what is of his owne forming. If the Scriptures were a rule formed by man, or by Angels, it were unſuffera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſubject the ſpirit of God to any rule ſo infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely below it ſelfe, but, <hi>All Scripture being of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine inſpiration, holy men of God ſpeaking as they were moved by the holy Ghoſt,</hi> as it is of great uſe to us againſt the wiles of the Devill; ſo it is a particular honour to the ſpirit of God, which by the meanes of ſuch a Standard, and rule, appeares ever like it ſelfe, that is, uniforme, and conſtant, and which is a high attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute of God, without variableneſſe and ſhadow of changing.</p>
            <p>From this good underſtanding betweene the ſpirit of God, and the word of God, the Scriptures dicta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:117372:8"/>
by the ſame ſpirit, it is that in all matter of faith and worſhip and all things ſpirituall, the appeale is ſtill to the Scriptures, as to the viſible and lawfull Judge. So Chriſt convincing the <hi>Jewes</hi> of their ſin of unbeliefe, tels them, <hi>There is one that accuſeth them even Moſes, for he wrote of him, John</hi> 5.45. And as for the <hi>Jewes,</hi> ſo for all others, our Lord ſaith, <hi>That he that rejecteth him, and receiveth not his word, hath one that judgeth him;</hi> the Word, ſaith hee, <hi>that I have ſpoken, the ſame ſhall judge him in the laſt day.</hi> So <hi>Paul</hi> gloryes in this, that the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> received the word ſpoken by them, <hi>not as the word of man</hi> (a thing ſubject to exceptions and limitations) <hi>but as it is in truth the word of God, which effectually worketh in them that beleeve,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.13. Hence, when Chriſt would convince the <hi>Sadduces</hi> of the Reſurrection, he told them, <hi>They erred, not knowing the Scriptures, nor the power of God, Matth.</hi> 22.29. and then makes out his aſſertion by Scripture authority, <hi>Have yee not read that which was ſpoken by God unto you;</hi> And then brings them the very Scripture words, <hi>I am the God of Abraham, &amp;c.</hi> verſ. 32. So when Chriſt would prove himſelf to be the <hi>Meſsiah,</hi> he bids them <hi>Search the Scriptures, John</hi> 5.39. You ſee therefore it is no diſparagement to the ſpirit of God, that there is a viſible Standard and Rule manifeſt to all men, to which we may have a conſtant, and eaſie recourſe in any doubt or controverſie of faith or worſhip.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>
               </label> If any ſhal object further, that though this be not a diſparagement or a leſſening to the ſpirit of GOD (ſince the authority of God it ſelfe, and the reaſon of the thing ſeems to vindicate it from this:) Yet the Scriptures are capable of ſenſes and interpretations
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:117372:8"/>
ſo various (as we ſee in all experience) as it will be difficult to make it a Sandard and Rule of Faith and Worſhip, or a <hi>Medium</hi> to try the ſpirits by, ſince it needs the aſſiſtance of the ſpirit, to the right inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> I anſwer, that the ignorance or perverſneſſe of Interpreters, can by no meanes take away that Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour from the Scriptures, that it ſhould not be the Standard and Rule in things ſpirituall; no more then in civill things, the ignorance or peruerſeneſſe of a man in giving the interpretations of the Law, ſhould detract from the honour of its being the rule and ſtandard of judging in things civill. It is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that in reſpect of the things ſpoken, or in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the Speaker, the Scripture hath not various and uncertaine ſenſes, but it ſeemes to have ſo often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, in reſpect of our vanity or ignorance: Which leads me into conſideration of the ſecond charge, I lay to ſome perverſe ſpirits of theſe times, which by obſcure and myſterious Allegories, draw a vaile, and caſt thick Clouds betweene us and the Scriptures; and then cry out, that they are myſterious, obſcure, darke, and hidden; but <hi>If our Goſpel bee hid</hi> (as the Apoſtle ſaith) <hi>it is hid to them that periſh, in whom the God of this World hath blinded their eyes:</hi> Pride, or ſome evill luſting hath blinded their eyes, and then they cry out, that there is a defect on the part of the object; that that is not viſible, and the way by which they would ſpiritualize and inlighten it, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders it a thouſand times darker, whilſt under a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of running far enough from the Letter which they judge carnall and killing, they ſubject it to the vanities and dreamings of every addle head, and make
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:117372:9"/>
the holy Scripture <hi>Eccho</hi> to the ſound that is already in their eares, according to that Engliſh Proverbe, As the foole thinketh, ſo the Bell tincketh.</p>
            <p>But firſt here they greatly miſtake who in alluding to that place of 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Not of the letter but of the ſpirit,</hi> thinke there is an oppoſition put betwixt the letter of the Goſpel, and New Teſtament, and the ſpirituall ſenſe of it, for here plainely by Letter is meant the Law, and by ſpirit is meant the Goſpel, or New Teſtament in the very letter of it; as you have, <hi>John</hi> 1. <hi>The Law was given by Moſes, but grace and truth came by Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Not as if the Jewes were onely under a literall externall adminiſtration, which did not affect their ſpirits: God knew how to ſpeake to his in thoſe times, but that was not the office of <hi>Moſes,</hi> or of the Law, which propounded rules of living, with promiſes and threatnings; therefore, <hi>When the Law came, ſin revived and I dyed,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul;</hi> But the Miniſtry of the Goſpel he cals ſpirit, becauſe the things it declares, are quickning, enlivening, and reſtoring, and ſuch (as ſpeaking comparatively alſo) the ſpirit accompanies, much more then it did the Law, as being the inſtrument of the grace of Chriſt in his Miniſtry. The miſtake of this place, made <hi>Origen</hi> firſt, and ſince very many, looſe themſelves and their auditors in ſenſleſſe and idle Allegories, ſuppoſing that the allegoricall ſenſe was ſpirituall, and the literall killing; whereas the literall ſenſe in moſt ſcriptures, is not onely a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall ſenſe, but the onely ſpirituall ſenſe of it, and if beſides what ſenſe I have given of this place of the Law and the Goſpel, it reaches further; <hi>the letter and the ſpirit,</hi> is not to be underſtood of the Expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:117372:9"/>
of the words, but of the fruit and effect of it, it then being onely received in the Letter, when it af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects not the heart, nor workes ſaving changes upon us, and then in the ſpirit when it indeed converts, and turnes us and moulds us into that holy frame and forme to which God ordaines his people.</p>
            <p>Now that theſe expreſſions <hi>of the Spirit and the Letter,</hi> are meant particularly of the Law and the Goſpel, appeares evidently in the following verſes, 7, 8, 9. For <hi>verſe</hi> 7. ſpeaking of the Letter he calls it, <hi>The adminiſtration of death, written and engraven in ſtones,</hi> which we know was the Law; this hee proves glorious from the glory and ſhining of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> countenance: In oppoſition to this, he cals the Goſpel, <hi>The miniſtry of the ſpirit, verſe</hi> 8. and ſhews in one point more the excelling glory of this Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell beyond the Law, that it is to abide and remain evermore, whereas the other is done away and paſt; <hi>verſe</hi> 10, 11. It is true that what the Law is of it ſelf, that the Goſpel is by accident, killing and deſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ive, 2 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 2, 16. <hi>To the one we are the ſavour of death unto death, &amp;c.</hi> But though the Goſpel be the occaſion of damnation to very many, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it may be called the Spirit or Doctrine of life; for as much as God uſes it as the inſtrument or <hi>vehi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culum</hi> of our converſion or new life; and that it holds out, and offers free reconciliation to us with God, whereas the Law (taking it ſimply and alone as it is here taken) is <hi>the Letter that killeth;</hi> and the miniſtry of death preſcribing onely an exact rule of life (by which comes the knowledge and revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of ſinne which kills) without ſhewing any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leife or way to eſcape.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:117372:10"/>And thus have I briefly opened this place, which hath been the cauſe to many of ſuch groſſe errings and miſtakes.</p>
            <p>But to proceed; It is certaine the Scriptures have a plainneſſe and eaſineſſe in them to be underſtood, and therefore are ſaid to be, <hi>A light to our feet, and a Lanthorne to our paths; and a light ſhining in a darke place: Thy words they give light, they give underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the ſimple.</hi> And if this may be affirmed of the Writings of the Old Teſtament, with much more reaſon may it be affirmed of thoſe of the New. <hi>For Grace and Truth came by Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> They had ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things formerly in Types and Allegories, as things that concerned others more then themſelves, <hi>For it was revealed to them, that not unto themſelves, but unto us they did miniſter the things which are now reported unto you, by them that Preacht the Goſpell unto you,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.12. Therefore <hi>Moſes</hi> their Prophet was vayled to them, <hi>But we with open face, beholding as in a glaſſe the glory of the Lord, are changed from glory to glory,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.13, 18.</p>
            <p>Nor will it be to any purpoſe to object here, that which is affirmed by <hi>Peter,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.16. That <hi>ſome things in Pauls Epiſtles, are hard to be underſtood:</hi> For even thoſe things be made eaſie by diligence, prayer to God, communication and conference with others. God hath made in all things, indigency, the bond of Society, without we need one another, we ſhould not value and eſteeme one another, we ſhould not have love, nor converſe one with another. But who doth this difficulty or hardneſſe here ſpoken of, hurt? <hi>Men unlearned and unſtable;</hi> whoſe ſluggiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe makes unlearned, and whoſe corruption and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:117372:10"/>
depravement makes unſtable; men that are double in their ends, and therefore unſtable in their wayes, as appeares by their wreſting and deſtroying of the Scriptures, which is there ſpoken of; and not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thoſe hard places, but other Scriptures alſo to their owne deſtruction.</p>
            <p>But if there be any difficulty in Scripture-expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions (which God ſometimes permits for holy ends, as I have ſaid) will the way to helpe our ſelves be to fall a Figurizing and Allegorizing, making the Word of God ſapleſſe and fruitleſſe, by the vanity of our Traditions? Or becauſe (as the men I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine againſt uſe to doe) there are ſome figurative and allegoricall expreſſions in the New Teſtament, as when our Saviour calls himſelfe, <hi>a Vine, or a Doore</hi> (which figurative ſpeeches are to ordinary eares as eaſie to be underſtood as the moſt literall) ſhall we take liberty from hence to confound Heaven and Earth? And upon every itching of our owne fancy to diſſolve the whole Scripture and Word of God, into Figures and Allegories? Which in ſtead of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightning, brings us into clouds and darkneſſe; that in that miſt the Devill may uſe as he will. I will not deny, but ſome things are to be expounded alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorically.</p>
            <p>The legall Ceremonies may be handled allegori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally, becauſe they were ſhadows and types of good things to come, as the Paſchall Lambe of Chriſt <hi>Chriſt our Paſſeover is ſacrificed for us,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.7: Chriſt was the ſcope and Butt of the Old Teſtament, and therefore the Paſchall Lambe, the brazen Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and a hundred other things are accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted juſtly to him, alſo ſeverall Hiſtories upon this
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:117372:11"/>
account have their allegoricall uſe, ſo there be a care had to preſerve the Hiſtoricall truth ſtable and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaken: So our Saviour accommodates the Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of <hi>Solomon</hi> and <hi>Jonas</hi> to himſelfe, as having be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the Hiſtoricall truth, an uſe of typifying out him in his office, and ſufferings; and if a man by way of alluſion or ſimilitude, will allegorize a Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory, as to ſay that as <hi>David</hi> overcame <hi>Goliah,</hi> ſo Chriſt doth the Devill, ſo the ſpirit doth the fleſh, if it be done pertinently, may have its uſe. But with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all queſtion, the literall ſenſe of Scripture, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially of the New Teſtament is principally to be ſought after, as that you may ſafely build upon for Doctrines, Exhortations, and Concluſions, <hi>Symbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lica Theologia non eſt argumentativa;</hi> except ſuch as the holy Ghoſt propounds and interprets, in which caſe wee may ſafely follow and conclude from Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legories.</p>
            <p>I would not therefore expound any Scriptures allegorically (except as before) but ſuch as could not be expounded literally; as for inſtance, When without the ſuppoſition of a type or figure the Scriptures would imply a falſhood; or when in a Gramaticall ſenſe, the words of the Scripture would imply an abſurdity, as that Chriſt is a Doore, or a Vine; or when the literall ſenſe is contradictory to a rule of Faith, as when we are commanded to pull out an eye, or to cut off a hand, or foot, but to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part needleſly from the Gramatical and literall ſenſe of Scripture, to ſubtelize it with Figures and Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gories, is that which deſtroyes the majeſty and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity of the Word of God, makes it a Noſe of Wax, and ſubjects it to the fancies of every craſie
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:117372:11"/>
and unſound braine; ſo that as in another caſe one complaines, they doe <hi>Verborum minutiis rerum fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere pondera.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if it be objected (as it is by ſome) that if the literall and Gramaticall ſenſe, be the Scripture ſenſe, the naturall man may be very able, in under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding Scripture.</p>
            <p>I Anſwer, that no queſtion they may, and to their greater condemnation, but yet they want the glory and life of this underſtanding, which is the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all impreſſion affecting their hearts, and making them <hi>God like.</hi> Thoſe things which are words of life and peace to one, are but a dead letter to them, there wants that infuſion into the words, which makes them mighty and converting, <hi>Changing them from darkneſſe to light, and from the power of Satan to God;</hi> to one, it is <hi>the word of Men,</hi> to others, it is <hi>the word of God, the power of God to ſalvation, effectually work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in them that beleeve.</hi> Whereas thoſe abſurd Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legorizers we complaine of, boaſt of the ſpirit, and revelations, and thinke they have got all, when they have mudded, and defiled, and nonſenſifyed a Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture with their Figures and Allegories, though they feele nothing of the ſpirit and life, which ſhould change and convert them into the forme of Doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine delivered to them. And according to this ſenſe muſt ſeverall Scriptures be accommodated; parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly, that, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14. <hi>The naturall man receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not the things of the ſpirit of God, for they are foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhneſſe unto him, neither can hee know them becauſe they are ſpiritually diſcerned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That which we tranſlate the naturall man, is in the Greek <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>animalis,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ab anima,</hi> the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:117372:12"/>
ſoule, ſo as he is a <hi>naturall</hi> or <hi>an animall man</hi> which walkes according to ſenſe, or to the fleſh, that judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of things after a carnall and humane reaſoning; other things are fooliſhneſſe to him, ſo you have it in the 23. of the former Chapter, <hi>We Preach Chriſt crucified to the Greeks fooliſhneſſe,</hi> And in the words of the Text, <hi>The things of the ſpirit of God are fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe unto him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet the notion of Chriſt Crucified, as it is layd downe in Scripture in plaine and ſignificant words, is certainely intelligible to an animall man; but the ſpirituall reaſon of it, which is the beauty and glory of it, which ſhould alter and convert, and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, by beholding that he ſees not; and therefore though cuſtome and commonneſſe have taken away the ſeeming abſurdity of ſuch a notion, ſo as men can beare it, and take it up, and profeſſe it with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; yet the ſpirituall beauty of it, which is the taking and converting thing, they ſee not. As the eye of ſenſe ſees the figure and ſuperficies of a thing, but cannot tell the reaſon of it, for want of a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple to judge by; ſo a naturall man that hath no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther principles but ſenſe and reaſon, ſees the truth aright, and as it is; but it is a fooliſh and weak thing to him, in order to the end for which it is appointed, becauſe there is a ſpirituall beauty which he hath no eye to ſee, nor ſenſe to taſte.</p>
            <p>I deny not, beſides this, but that when there are diverſities of interpretations and allegoricall ſenſes, of which I ſpake before; the ſpirituall man hath ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of all the World beſides, and that not onely in the ſenſe of which I have already ſpoken; but in oppoſition to one more rayſed, and more ſpirituall,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:117372:12"/>
a man may be called a naturall or carnall man, ſo you have it in the beginning of the next Chapter, <hi>And I brethren could not ſpeake unto you as unto ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, but as unto carnall, even as unto babes in Chriſt,</hi> verſe 3. <hi>For yee are yet carnall, for whereas there is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you, envyings, and diviſions, and ſtrife, are yee not carnall and walke as men?</hi> Which as it ſhewes that the oppoſition of ſpirituall to carnall, may be made in reſpect of more or leſſe ſpiritualneſſe in the ſame party; ſo it leads us backe to that ſenſe I gave be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore:</p>
            <p>That he is to be judged the ſpirituall man, and to comprehend beſt the myſterie of Divine things, and of the holy Scriptures, not who can moſt miſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly (that is, as theſe men uſe it, obſcurely and aenigmatically, and if you will irrationally, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdly) diſcourſe of Divine things, and of inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of Scripture; but he, <hi>Who laying aſide all malice and ſuperfluity of naughtineſſe, receives the word,</hi> and he who by ſeeing and beholding it, is transfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med into that which is moſt oppoſite to envying, ſtrife, and diviſions.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle <hi>Jude,</hi> after he hath made a liſt of the worſt and vileſt of men, <hi>Uncleane perſons that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe Dominion, and ſpeake evill of Dignities;</hi> he tels you, <hi>verſe</hi> 10. That <hi>theſe are ſenſuall, or animall, or naturall</hi> (for it is the ſame word that is uſed here) <hi>having not the ſpirit;</hi> Theſe were all Chriſtians, and Profeſſors, and perhaps could Philoſophate as my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteriouſly as their neighbours, for they were ſuch as <hi>ſeparated themſelves, verſe</hi> 10. and it is like were well opinionated of their abilities; but becauſe the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Word gained them not to the love of God,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:117372:13"/>
what ever light they had beſides could not defend them from the denomination of <hi>ſenſuall</hi> or <hi>animall,</hi> which is the word here oppoſed to ſpirituall.</p>
            <p>And thus have I done with what I intend to ſay, in anſwer to the objection above made. To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with what I firſt mentioned in this point of the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>The ſpirit of God, and the Word of God the holy Scriptures, hold ſo good an intelligence, as we try the ſpirits by the Scriptures, and the holy ſpirit enlightens us to underſtand the Scriptures; ſo Chriſt by his ſpirit inlightened the Diſciples go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>Emaus</hi> to underſtand the Scriptures; hee did not make them wiſe without them, which he could have done, but he choſe that <hi>medium</hi> as a <hi>vehiculum</hi> of his ſpirit ſutable and proportionable to them, and to his wayes and diſpenſations towards his people.</p>
            <p>In like manner when <hi>Paul</hi> had exhorted the <hi>Theſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalonians, not to quench the Spirit,</hi> he doth not lead them from the Word of God to vaine ſpeculati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but immediatly ſubjoynes a command, <hi>Not to deſpiſe Prophecy;</hi> intimating, an aptneſſe in men under the notion of magnifying and advancing of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to deſpiſe Prophecy; and ſhewing alſo that the meanes to quench and extinguiſh the illuminations of the ſpirit, is to have low and unworthy thoughts of the Word of God, and of Prophecying, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Analogy and Proportion of that Word.</p>
            <p>Now as ſome think it an indignity to try the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit by the Scripture, and others with vaine allego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizing, make the Word of God of none effect (to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:117372:13"/>
both which I have ſpoken already) ſo there doth not want of them which thinke the uſe of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath its period and time with men, beyond which it is uſeleſſe and improper to attend to it, though before that time it be a duty and of uſe to us. According to this ſenſe they interpret that place of <hi>Peter,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19. Where the Apoſtle, ſpeaking of the Scripture of the Prophets, tels them to whom he writes, That <hi>they doe well to take heed to them as to a light ſhining in a darke place, till the day dawne, and the day ſtarre ariſe in their hearts:</hi> That is, till God have ſet up ſuch a light in them, as they need no more helpe of Propheſie; according to which interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, they adapt alſo other Scriptures, as that of <hi>John</hi> 6. quoted out of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 54.13. <hi>They ſhall all be taught of God,</hi> that of <hi>Jeremiah</hi> 31.34. <hi>They ſhall teach no more every man his neighbour, and every man his brother, ſaying, Know the Lord, for they ſhall all know me from the leaſt of them to the greateſt of them;</hi> and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly alſo that place of <hi>John,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.20, 21, 27. <hi>But yee have an unction from the holy one, and yee ſhall know all things:</hi> Verſe 27. <hi>But the anoynting which yee have received of him abideth in you, and ye need not that any man teach you, but as the ſame anoynting teacheth you all things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To ſpeak a little to theſe places, and firſt to ſpeak ſomething to this laſt of <hi>John:</hi> The Apoſtle ſeemes to doe two things, one is to bring what he ſayes to the <hi>examen</hi> of the ſpirit, who onely is the full and ſufficient judge; who ſeales to our ſpirits, to the end that wee may be certaine that God ſpeakes it: Secondly, he would the better authorize his doctrine by referring them to the judgement of the ſpirit
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:117372:14"/>
within them which teaches them, that finding ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that beares witneſſe within to the word, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it might have a full effect upon their ſpirits, and worke in them a ſtrong perſwaſion. But then parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly, and perhaps eſpecially in this place, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſeems modeſtly to excuſe himſelf for ſeeming to deale with them as with learners, and beginners, when as he tells them they have the unction of the ſpirit, and know all things: In like manner is that which <hi>Paul</hi> ſayes, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.14. and to the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe when he tels them, that <hi>they were full of goodneſſe and filled with all knowledge, and able alſo to admoniſh one another;</hi> and yet he tels them, he thought it his duty to admoniſh them, to put them in minde as he ſayes; ſo here, <hi>Verſe</hi> 21. <hi>I have not written unto you, becauſe ye know not the truth, but becauſe ye know it.</hi> For if they had beene altogether unlearned, and unbot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom'd and had not knowne ſomething, if they had not had foundations layd, and been principled, they had not beene fit for the Doctrine hee delivered: Whereas he ſayes, <hi>Verſe</hi> 21. <hi>They knew all things,</hi> that cannot bee taken in the full extent that the words ſeeme to beare, for <hi>we know but in part,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. but either with reſtriction to the ſubject in hand, or elſe to ſhew as before, that he doth rather remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber them and admoniſh them of ſuch things as hee writ, then altogether lay foundations or deliver principles that are new to them, and with which they are not acquainted. Therefore <hi>Verſe</hi> 24. hee admoniſheth them that <hi>that might remaine with them which they have heard from the beginning,</hi> as intending rather to confirme what they knew already, and have been taught from the beginning by the word and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:117372:14"/>
ſpirit, then to add in this exhortation any thing in which they were raw and unprincipled.</p>
            <p>But becauſe <hi>John</hi> ſayes here, that <hi>they have an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction from the ſpirit and know all things;</hi> and Verſ. 27 that <hi>they need not that any man ſhould teach them:</hi> To conclude that therefore they needed no other Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry or teaching but the ſpirit, neither Scriptures, nor Propheſies, were to make <hi>John</hi> himſelfe ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous: For wherefore did he labour in this Doctrine, and wherefore did he teach them at all, if there were no need at all of his, teaching, when <hi>Paul</hi> ſayes (as he doth) 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.9. <hi>Touching brotherly love, there is no need that I write unto you, for yee your ſelves are taught of God to love one another:</hi> Doth he forbeare therefore to exhort the Saints to that duty, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhew that he need not doubt of the ſucceſſe of that Doctrine of brotherly love (which he and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Apoſtles inculcates exceedingly) becauſe they have a principle taught them by God himſelfe and his holy ſpirit that renders them apt to receive any hints or intimations that way.</p>
            <p>It is a great piece of Oratory, when yee can per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade your hearers that the things ye would inforce and make out more fully, they aſſent unto already. Therefore <hi>John</hi> here profeſſes that hee wrote to them, <hi>becauſe they knew the truth already,</hi> and upon that very ground, that <hi>they were taught, and did know, and that they needed not teaching;</hi> he was incouraged to the Doctrine and exhortation he gave them. It is one of the beſt arguments we draw from reaſon, to prove there is a God, and in the vertue of which we uſe many others, that this point is a thing they need not to be taught, this they are all taught of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:117372:15"/>
God, no man ſo barbarous, no Nation ſo remote from the knowledge and converſe with others, that hath not this ingrafted in their nature, this notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, we doe not ceaſe to multiply arguments to this purpoſe, to confirme and draw out that prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple into uſe and practice, of which there is ſo faire a beginning layd deep, even in the nature of every man living.</p>
            <p>The ſumme is (beſides what I have ſayd in the beginning that the Apoſtle would uſe them to bring all things to the <hi>Examen</hi> of the ſpirit, and that he would improve the confirmation of the truth of his Doctrine by the principles already layd in them by the ſpirit of God) he uſes theſe expreſſions, <hi>that they know all things, and need not that any man teach them, but as the ſame anoynting teaches them, and that he writes to them, becauſe they know the truth alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy;</hi> Both to avoyd the ſeeming to deale with them as learners, and beginners, altogether unprincipled and untaught, when as the things were ſuch as were built upon principles, layd into them by the anoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the ſpirit, as alſo to fetch an effectuall riſe of arguments for the aſſenting to ſuch things as they knew and were taught already; as there is no better bottome argument (as I ſayd) to prove there is a God, then this, that they know it already, being all taught it of God, nor no better foundation to the exhortation of brotherly love, with which the Scripture abounds above any one thing, then that which <hi>Paul</hi> layes in the place above quoted out of the <hi>Theſſalonians;</hi> That there is no need to bee taught that, <hi>For that they are all taught of God to love one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> We ſay it is the part of a wiſe man; <hi>Rerum ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtarum
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:117372:15"/>
cauſas quaerere,</hi> and it is eſpecially the duty of thoſe who have the care of inſtructing others to improve principles already lodged into them of which the foundations are moſt generally and moſt cleerly layd by the holy ſpirit in all the Saints, for thoſe commonly are of the greateſt uſe and concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. So as here will be no good warant to depart from the uſe of Scripture, or the Miniſtry of teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (for which God hath in all times, and in theſe particularly in which <hi>John</hi> wrote, indued men with gifts, and power) to follow vaine Enthuſiaſmes, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe we wil put ridiculous and contradictory actions and wayes upon the Doctrines of this holy Apoſtle, and the dictates of the holy ſpirit.</p>
            <p>Having largely and ſufficiently I hope, opened theſe words, I proceed now to thoſe other texts I quoted out of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> and <hi>Jeremiah.</hi> That of <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah</hi> is in <hi>Chap.</hi> 31. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 31. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which is certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Propheſie of thoſe times in which the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> lived, and of that ſtate of the Church in which in the place before diſcuſſed he ſpeaks.</p>
            <p>Here the Prophet (as it was uſuall with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> and the reſt riſing from the Type to the Antitype) having before diſcourſed of the inlarg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and bettering of the condition of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> he fals naturally and eaſily into the diſcourſe of the times of the Goſpell and New Teſtament. <hi>Behold, the day's come ſaith the Lord, that I will make a new Covenant, &amp;c.</hi> what this Covenant is not, hee tells you, Verſe 32. <hi>Not the Covenant hee made with their Fathers, when he brought them out of the Land of Aegypt.</hi> What that Covenant was, we ſhall not need here to conſider of; but then Verſe 33. hee tells you what
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:117372:16"/>
his Covenant ſhall be, <hi>I will put my Law in their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward parts, and write it in their hearts, and I will bee their God and they ſhall be my people, and they ſhall teach no more every man his neighbour, and every man his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſaying, Know the Lord; for they ſhall all know me from the leaſt of them to the greateſt of them, ſaith the Lord, for I will forgive their iniquity, and I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member their ſins no more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The great benefit of this New Covenant in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to the Old, lyes in this, that in this New Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant God doth not onely propound the tearmes, but ingages himſelfe to performe the condition, whereas the Old Covenant ſet before you life and death, good and evill, but ingaged you to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of the good without aſſiſtance (for the Law was without you) or to the ſuffering of evill. But in the new Covenant, the Law is within, written in your hearts, by which you are made holy and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed for all good. If you ſinne <hi>(as if any man ſayes he has no ſin he deceives himſelfe, and the truth is not in him) He will forgive your iniquity, and remember your ſin no more.</hi> And becauſe the knowledge of God and his wayes is of the greateſt conſideration to us, for our happineſſe and holineſſe, ye ſhall be enlightened, have the holy unction, and be taught of God. This inlightening (eſpecially in things of the greateſt concernment, as that inſtanced in here, <hi>Knowing the Lord;</hi> that is, with a practicall knowledge, ſuch as changes the heart and converts) is ſo much the work of God himſelf, and of the holy ſpirit, as of the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall and chiefe agent, that the ſubordinate inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments who contribute under God, by the will and inſtitution of God to that work are ſcarce conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:117372:16"/>It is well knowne, this being the promiſe of the New Covenant, the time of opening and beginning of which was after the death and reſurrection of Chriſt, as <hi>Heb.</hi> 8. <hi>Chriſt became the mediator of a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Covenant:</hi> It is knowne I ſay, that in thoſe times (in the courſe of which we live) there was the inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of <hi>Apoſtles, Prophets, Paſtors, and Teachers, for the perfecting of the Saints, for the worke of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, for the edifying of the body of Chriſt, Epheſ.</hi> 4. and 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.2. <hi>Paul</hi> commanded him there, <hi>To preach the Word, and to be inſtant in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon;</hi> and <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. <hi>How ſhall they beleeve in him of whom they have not heard, and how ſhall they heare without a prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher;</hi> ſo that gifts and Offices and teaching were judged by the holy Ghoſt, extreame neceſſaries to faith, holineſſe, and the right knowledge of God in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>This notwithſtanding in reſpect of that great part the holy ſpirit acts, the agency and working of men deſerves ſcarce a thought or mention, ſo as on that conſideration it may be ſayd not to be. And it is not unuſuall (as elſewhere) ſo in Scripture phraſe that that ſhould be affirmed of one, and den<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed of others, which more illuſtriouſly or more frequently appeares in that one, though in ſome ſort it be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon with others. It is certaine <hi>Iſaack</hi> loved <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau</hi> too, but becauſe he more loved <hi>Eſau,</hi> its ſayd, <hi>Iſaack loved Eſau, and Rebecca loved Jacob, Gen.</hi> 25.28. And though Chriſt loved all the Diſciples, it is ſaid notwithſtanding that <hi>John</hi> was <hi>the Diſciple whom Jeſus loved.</hi> But eſpecially that place of <hi>Matth.</hi> 15. where Chriſt ſayes, <hi>He was not ſent but to the loſt ſheepe of the houſe of Iſrael;</hi> and yet if Chriſt were
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:117372:17"/>
not ſent as well to the <hi>Gentiles</hi> as to the <hi>Jewes,</hi> it were little for our comfort.</p>
            <p>The preaching of the Word, how neceſſary ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to the begetting of faith <hi>(for how can they beleeve in him, on whom they have not heard, and how can they heare without a Preacher)</hi> yet how little doth it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute, and how truely may ſo great an effect be ſayd to bee alone from God. What can the ſound of words doe, but ſtrike the eare, but it is the unction, that muſt affect the heart. 'Tis not the noyſe of a voice without, but ſomething within, that produces ſuch great and mighty effects. The great weight that turnes the ballance, and that <hi>ignea vis,</hi> that fire that inflames the mind, and carryes it up to God, to move after God, to follow God, is ſome greater and higher thing then the voyce of man or ſound of words, and is nothing elſe but the unction within us, and the voyce of God himſelfe.</p>
            <p>In a word, it is the effect of that which is here, and more particularly in <hi>Iſaiah</hi> promiſed; That <hi>they ſhould be all taught of God;</hi> which place as it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded and applyed by our Saviour (the beſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitor) will give the ſureſt witneſſe to the expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion we have given of this: The place is, <hi>John</hi> 13.45, <hi>It is written in the Prophets, they ſhall be all taught of God, every man therefore that hath heard and hath learned of the Father cometh to me.</hi> Our Saviour ſeemes to have reſpect to the place we have been ſpeaking of all this while, where God undertakes to do ſo much as he makes the Miniſtry of man in compariſon no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, or more eſpecially to that place in <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 54.13. where the Prophet ſpeaking of the reſtauration of the Church, affirmes, that <hi>their Children ſhall bee
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:117372:17"/>
taught of God.</hi> Now when our Saviour comes to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply and improve this paſſage of the Prophet, doth he reject the Miniſtry of man, as a thing of no uſe, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together carnall and unprofitable? Doth he repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate Preaching, Exhortation, and Doctrine? No ſuch thing: He himſelfe Preach't, that hee was the <hi>Meſsiah</hi> that was to come, and he ſent our Apoſtles, and Diſciples, <hi>to Teach and Baptize,</hi> promiſing great rewards to thoſe that ſhall not onely propheſie, but <hi>ſhall receive a Prophet in his Name;</hi> ſo farre was hee from aboliſhing the uſe of the Miniſtry, or the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gency or aſſiſtance of men, in that great worke of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting and improving faith, but tells the <hi>Jewes,</hi> to whom he ſpake, and who were offended with him, for the meanneſſe of his birth and condition, that the reaſon why they beleeved not, was becauſe they fell not under that great promiſe, <hi>To be taught of God: That no man could come to him, except the Father drew him.</hi> That teaching of God was eſpecially neceſſary, and that drawing of God, that ſecret language, and thoſe inviſible Cords without which all the words of man, no of the man <hi>Jeſus</hi> would doe no good, nor contribute effectually to ſo great and high an end as comming to <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and beleeving in him. So as cleerly the uſe of this and other Scriptures of this kind is farre from excluding the Miniſtry of man, and the uſe of the Scriptures and other Ordinances, which the wiſedome of God in the dayes of this new Covenant, hath made extreamely neceſſary and uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to us; but to ſhew us where we muſt expect the Energy, force, and power, which as an infuſion into theſe Ordinances, muſt produce theſe bleſſed effects, and to give us an account of the difference that is
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:117372:18"/>
found amongſt men under the ſame Ordinances and diſpenſations, that ſome come to God in Chriſt, and forſake all things for him, and others lye ſtill dead in their ſinnes for want of this Unction, this being taught of God, and of this ſtrong and powerfull drawing which our Saviour ſpeaks of in this place.</p>
            <p>Having ſpoken that which is ſufficient to the places laſt treated on, I come now to that which I firſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded out of 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19. but this yet wee have gained already (if wee aſſent to the expoſitions gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven) that the higheſt teachings we are capable of in this life, the teachings of God, and of the anointings of the ſpirit, are nothing of <hi>Superſedeas</hi> to the teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of others, or to our owne reading, and medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation in the Word of God. So as according to the truth already made out, this Scripture will receive the eaſier accommodation.</p>
            <p>Firſt, It is generally believed, that thoſe two Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles were written to the <hi>Jewes,</hi> of whom <hi>Peter</hi> was more particularly the Miniſter, and the Apoſtle: that this ſecond Epiſtle was writ to the ſame perſons to whom the firſt was, appeares by the firſt Verſe of the third Chapter, <hi>This ſecond Epiſtle, beloved, I now write unto you, &amp;c.</hi> Now the firſt Epiſtle is intituled, <hi>To the Strangers ſcattered abroad,</hi> which <hi>James</hi> in his inſcription calls, <hi>The twelve Tribes ſcattered abroad, James</hi> 1. For the <hi>Gentiles</hi> were not ſtrangers in thoſe Countreys which <hi>Peter</hi> mentions, but the <hi>Jews</hi> which dwelt in them. So as by <hi>the diſperſed ſtrangers, or the ſtrangers of the diſperſion,</hi> were meant the <hi>Jews.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peter</hi> therefore writing to the <hi>Jewes</hi> his Countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and of whom he was the Apoſtle, exhorts them to conſtancy in the Faith, and profeſſion of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:117372:18"/>
delivered to them by the Apoſtles. This hee inforces from an argument of the excellency of that Doctrine, the ſubject of which he calls <hi>the power and comming of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, Verſe</hi> 16. by which he underſtands his comming in the fleſh, and putting forth his power for the ſalvation of his people. He further inforces this exhortation from an argument fetcht from the certainety of this Doctrine, which had for his author Chriſt, and God, and was <hi>not cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly advanced by deviſed Fables, and ſophiſticall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> but <hi>we were eye-witneſſes of his majeſty,</hi> ſayes hee, <hi>Verſe</hi> 16. and heard alſo <hi>the voyce that came from the excellent glory,</hi> ſaying, <hi>this is my beloved ſonne in whom I am well pleaſed.</hi> So that as <hi>John</hi> ſayes, <hi>what wee have heard and ſeene, that declare wee unto you.</hi> Another argument which he uſes to confirme them in this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent doctrine is the conſent of ancient propheſies, to the Jews well knowne, <hi>verſ.</hi> 19. We have alſo a more ſure word of Propheſie. <hi>Beza</hi> tranſlates it <hi>Non firmiorem ſed firmiſsimum ſermonem propheticum,</hi> and ſhewes the parallell of other Scriptures, where the Comparative is uſed for the Superlative. But if you read it not <hi>moſt ſure,</hi> but <hi>more ſure,</hi> it is in reſpect of thoſe to whom he writes, the Jewes, amongſt whom the Writings of the Prophets were of the greateſt and higheſt authority: <hi>Whereunto you doe well that you take heed as to a light ſhining in a darke place, till the day dawne and the day ſtarre ariſe in your hearts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Doctrine of the Prophets, which in <hi>Verſe</hi> 20. he commends from the infallibility of it, as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the ſpirit for its authour is another argument for the aſſerting and proving of that great truth which he mentions, <hi>Verſe</hi> 16. <hi>(Viz.) The comming of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:117372:19"/>
our Lord Jeſus Chriſt with power, &amp;c.</hi> For both argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments confirme the ſame thing, this from Propheſie and that from the voice of God; to wit, <hi>That Jeſus Chriſt was the Sonne of God, come in the fleſh for the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of the World.</hi> He tells them therefore, they doe well to make uſe of this head of argument, and to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to it, for it is <hi>like a light ſhining in a darke place:</hi> the propheticall Scripture, like a Lanthorne (as the word is) had a narrow and reſtrained light, and the times before the comming of Chriſt were times of darkneſſe; whereas the light of the Goſpell is more day light, like the morning ſtarre that chaſeth away darkneſſe, and this was true in the very beginning of the Goſpell to thoſe who had received it, in the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of it; and ſo yee have it, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.8. <hi>The dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is paſt, and the true light now ſhineth.</hi> If therefore you attend to the Scripture of the Prophets, which had for author not any private or particular ſpirit, but the ſpirit of God, you will have a light to guide you in your darkneſſe, till the day at laſt appeare, and the morning Starre, the ſigne thereof, ſcatter alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether your darkneſſe; that is, till the light of the Goſpell (which hee compares with that of former Propheſies) bring a clearneſſe and a brightneſſe, like to day light, in ſtead of the Candle, or Torch-light, yee enjoyed before; ſo as there ſhall be no doubt or ſcruple in you concerning this great my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of godlineſſe, aſſerted by the voice of Heaven, and confirmed by propheticall predictions, <hi>ſcilicet, Chriſt manifeſted in the fleſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if you ſay here, that the Jewes to whom hee writ, being beleevers, were cleare in this point alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: I anſwer, that it is more then appeares: That
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:117372:19"/>
there was a day light clearneſſe, yee have it in the 17 <hi>Acts</hi> 10. That <hi>thoſe that received the Word with all readineſſe of minde, ſearcht the Scriptures dayly, to ſee whether thoſe things were ſo.</hi> And yet as yee may ſee in a parallell place to this, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.41. They who <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily,</hi> or as it is there, <hi>gladly received the Word were Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized,</hi> which implyed them Beleevers, that being the condition of Baptiſme: So although theſe Jewes were already Beleevers in Chriſt, as having readily and gladly received the Word, yet it would be migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily to their advantage and eſtabliſhment, that they ſhould ſearch the Scriptures, and attend to the Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the Prophets, that ſo there might a day light clearneſſe, and aſſurance, concerning matters of this great moment ariſe in their hearts: So as many of the Jews that beleeved, amongſt which number ſome of theſe might be, were not come to that clearneſſe in beleeving, to which the preaching of the Goſpell, joyned to the ſearch of Scriptures would bring them.</p>
            <p>Nor here, doth the Apoſtle at all give a tearme or period to the ſearching or attending to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or written propheſies, but ſhewes the great uſe of them for the attaining the ends above mentioned. Wee know things are preſerved by the ſame way by which they are form'd, or procur'd. No man will deny me, that <hi>Timothy</hi> had attained a great degree in the knowledge of God and Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paul had no man like minded to him, who naturally cared for the things of the Lord.</hi> A man he was deſtin'd to great workes by propheſie, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.18. Gifted alſo and inabled for his Miniſtry, by propheſie and laying on of hands, and inſtructed in the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:117372:20"/>
from a Child. And yet this <hi>Timothy</hi> forearmed already by Propheſie, and gifts, and ſtudy in the Scriptures, is commanded, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.13. <hi>to give at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance to reading,</hi> and in the 15 <hi>Verſe</hi> he is comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>to meditate upon thoſe things, and to be in them, and give himſelfe</hi> wholly <hi>to them, that his profiting might be evident and appeare to all:</hi> Nay <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe who gave the rule of <hi>not knowing Chriſt after the fleſh,</hi> and underſtood, ſurely, the myſtery of godlineſſe, as well as theſe men, in that very place where hee ſayes, <hi>that he is ready to be offered up, and that the time of his depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is at hand,</hi> 2 Tim. 4.6. When having fought a good fight, his thoughts runne of Crownes and glory <hi>Verſe</hi> 7, 8. commanded <hi>Timothy</hi> expreſly to bring with him when he came <hi>the Books which he left at Troas, and the parchments.</hi> That great Apoſtle was not of theſe mens minds, that it was a carnall and unſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all thing to read and meditate, and uſe ſuch helps, as God who knowes us better then wee doe our ſelves, judges meet for us, but is forward and ready himſelfe to doe what he exhorts <hi>Timothy</hi> to, to give himſelfe to reading and meditation, and thinke it no diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to uſe that meanes as well as others.</p>
            <p>And thus have I done with that which I propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to my ſelfe, to ſay concerning the Scriptures in order to the diſcourſe I have in hand.</p>
            <p>Thoſe things which in the next place come into conſideration, and need to bee vindicated from the diſhonour and ſcorne put upon them, by a Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of theſe Times, who impoſe their vaine and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle fancies under the name and title of Spiritual Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations, are Goſpell Ordinances, ſuch as Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Word, Baptiſme, the Lords Supper, Church
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:117372:20"/>
fellowſhip and aſſembling, with what ever inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions our Lord hath left to entertaine us with in this ſtate, whilſt we are abſent from the Lord, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in the body, whilſt wee live by faith and not by ſight.</p>
            <p>In order to this, that which I firſt pitcht my thoughts upon, was that place of the 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 1.21. <hi>For after that in the wiſedome of God, the World by wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome knew not God, it pleaſed God by the fooliſhneſſe of Preaching, to ſave them that beleeve;</hi> which ſeemes particularly to ſtrike at the Vanity of ſuch men, who being as little able as others in a way of wiſedome to know God, by the wiſedome of God, are yet ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly ſcandalized at the weakeneſſe and fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Preaching and other Ordinances of that kind.</p>
            <p>That I might the better diſcover the ſcope and drift of this place, I thought it would be neceſſary to conſider ſomething the coherence.</p>
            <p>In this Chapter therefore, after the uſuall ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations and gratulations in the nine firſt <hi>Verſes,</hi> in the tenth he falls upon the firſt ſubject which he han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles in this Epiſtle, to wit, the diſſentions and divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions which were amongſt the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> with which he charges them, <hi>Verſe</hi> 11, 12. and from which he dehorts them. Hee gives them this authority for what he charges them with, <hi>The houſhold of Cloe, Verſe</hi> 11. then ſhewes what their fault was, that they were taken, and captivated with the names of men, which though of good and holy men, was not lawfull, nor fit for them to be; nay not of Chriſt himſelfe, as if doting on his perſon after the fleſh, his words, his deeds, his miracles, ſhould be onely extold and mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:117372:21"/>
with the deſpiſing or villifying of the gifts, and miracles, and doctrines of others, though as Chriſt, God, Man, they proceed from him. This Chriſt ſeemes himſelfe to reprove in the young man, <hi>Matth.</hi> 19.16. One came and ſayd, <hi>Good Maſter, what good thing ſhall I doe? Why calleſt thou mee good</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>there is none good, &amp;c. But keepe thou the Commandements:</hi> Whereby Chriſt ſhewes that that which the man conſidered, was not ſo much God the chiefe good, and holineſſe the way of converſe with him, but look't upon him as ſome excellent and famous Maſter: <hi>Why calleſt thou me good?</hi> Why look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt thou ſo much upon my perſon, and outward man? Rather all acceptance of perſons layd aſide, mind my Doctrine. This <hi>knowing Chriſt after the fleſh,</hi> as a gifted man ſo indowed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with difference from others, <hi>Paul</hi> diſclaimes, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.16. he knew him not now, as a Preacher of the Goſpel, as a Miniſter converſing here on earth, full of excellent gifts and parts, of ſuch a ſpirit and nature, but in a divine and heavenly manner, as he that was the Captaine of their Salvation, that reconciled them to God, that dyed for them, and roſe againe, after ſuch a heavenly man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner he knew him, and therefore was to bee new him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, both in the manner of his knowledge, and the rule of his life, <hi>Verſe</hi> 15, 16, 17, 19.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Verſe</hi> 13. He tells them, this their factious diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſention ſhewes as if there were many Chriſts, many Goſpels, many Saviours of the World, whereas Chriſt is but one, and not divided; or as if they were baptized into another Name then Chriſts, for ſo they gave themſelves up as Diſciples to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Teachers and Miniſters, as if they held their
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:117372:21"/>
Baptiſme of them, or they were Crucyfied for them.</p>
            <p>I thanke God, ſaith he, it is fallen out by a good providence, that I have baptized a very few, <hi>Leaſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhould ſay I had baptized in my owne name;</hi> That is, I had formed mee a Generation of followers and ſect of Diſciples: For that was, it ſeemes, a corrupt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion amongſt them, that thoſe who baptized ſhould be followed and adored by them as their ſpirituall Father and Maſter, <hi>Verſe</hi> 17. <hi>For Chriſt ſent me not to baptize, but to Preach the Goſpell:</hi> that is, the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall piece of my Miniſtry to which I was adorned with ſuch gifts and graces, and miracles, was Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Baptiſme indeed was an appendix of preaching and was in the Apoſtolicall Commiſſion, but being every ones worke as the ſerving of Tables, was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted when it grew burthenſome to others, that the Apoſtles might give themſelves to the word and prayer. For converſion from Atheiſme, and Juda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſme, being the great worke, the adminiſtration of the Seales which needed not thoſe gifts nor labour, was done ordinarily by other hands; ſo <hi>Peter</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed the houſe of <hi>Cornelius,</hi> but hee commanded them to be baptized by others, <hi>Acts</hi> 10. So Chriſt Preached, but his Diſciples Baptized, <hi>John</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paul</hi> had Commiſſion to Baptize, elſe hee would not have baptized any, but not principally: Suitable to this is that place, <hi>Jer.</hi> 7.22. <hi>I ſpake not to your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, concerning burnt offerings and ſacrifices, but this thing I commanded them, obey my voyce, &amp;c.</hi> Although in <hi>Aegypt</hi> they ſacrificed the Paſſeover, and in Mount <hi>Sinai</hi> hee commanded them concerning Sacrifices, but the other was the principall: Like alſo unto
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:117372:22"/>
which is that phraſe, <hi>I will have mercy and not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice;</hi> that is, I require mercy rather, and more principally then ſacrifice: So the Apoſtle ſayd, <hi>It was not meet for them to leave the word of God, and to ſerve tables;</hi> yet <hi>Paul</hi> did gather money for the poore Saints at <hi>Hieruſalem;</hi> that is, that was not their chief and ordinary worke, but the other.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Not with wiſedome of words, &amp;c.</hi> He had no ſooner made mention of Preaching the Goſpel, but he taxes the principall vice of theſe Sectaries, which was a certaine vanity in preaching the Goſpel, not onely with Rhetoricall inlargements and expreſſions, but even ſo Philoſophating the Goſpel, as they made it hold rather of humane wiſedome, then that divine ſimplicity which became ſo holy and heavenly a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject. <hi>Leaſt the Croſſe of Chriſt, &amp;c.</hi> that is, leaſt the Goſpell of Chriſt Crucified ſhould be rendred vaine and uſeleſſe, as needing the power of humane wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to uphold it.</p>
            <p>Verſe 18. <hi>For the preaching of the Croſſe, is to them that periſh fooliſhneſſe:</hi> This preaching of Chriſt cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, or a crucified Saviour, ſeemes to proud, and ſeeming wiſe men, the fooliſheſt thing in the world, that a dying man ſhould give life to others, that hee that could not ſave himſelfe, ſhould ſave the World. <hi>But unto us who are ſaved, &amp;c.</hi> Thoſe who being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtinate to eternall life, beleeve and are ſaved, they feele it is the power of God; and what is a more ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable effect of power, and of God, then that a cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified Saviour, by a company of illiterate poore men ſhould render the ſpirit quiet and ſtable in God, and give that converſion in life, which all the learned diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes of Philoſophers were not able to doe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:117372:22"/>Verſe 19. <hi>For it is written, I will deſtroy the wiſedome of the wiſe, &amp;c.</hi> God hath reſolved on this long agoe, that by ſtrength no man ſhall prevaile; wiſe and prudent men in the buſineſſe of Religion ſhall be no more then others, ſo as you may aske where is the Scribe, and diſputer of this World, either of <hi>Jew</hi> or <hi>Gentile,</hi> their wiſedome is made folly, and in thoſe things wherein they have thought to be wiſe, they have ſhewed themſelves the weakeſt and fooliſheſt of any other.</p>
            <p>Verſe 21. <hi>For after that in the wiſedome of God, &amp;c.</hi> Here hee gives the reaſon why God hath made the Goſpell ſo oppoſite and contrary to humane wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, becauſe that <hi>the World in the wiſedome of God, by wiſedome knew not God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the World is meant the whole World conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles:</hi> To them both, God ſpake in ſeverall manners, in the morall Law, and viſions and apparitions, in the fabrick of Heaven and earth, the ſubordination of all things to their firſt cauſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But the World by wiſedome knew not God,</hi> in theſe things, in this wiſe and excellent way ſuitable to prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples in them which they might have improved, they knew him not, nor glorified him as God, though that which was inviſible was manifeſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>It pleaſed God,</hi> or ſeemed good to God: Here the ſinne was the abuſe of divine wiſedome, the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was the infatuation of humane wiſedome; ſo as <hi>by the fooliſhneſſe of preaching, God would ſave them that beleeve:</hi> By that which to carnall and wiſe men, was the fooliſheſt thing in the Word, the ſimple and plaine preaching of a crucified Saviour, by that
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:117372:23"/>
it pleaſed God to ſave them that beleeve, that deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their owne wiſedome, and renouncing wholly themſelves, did beleeve that God could by the moſt weake, fooliſh, and unlikely <hi>mediums,</hi> produce the greateſt and moſt conſiderable effects.</p>
            <p>From this place thus conſidered, it will evidently follow, that worldly humane wiſedome in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and judging of God and heavenly things, is a fooliſh uſeleſſe thing, and that the fooliſhneſſe of preaching, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are the meanes of the ſalvation of the Elect. And that alſo which I lay eſpecially to the charge of theſe men, That the Goſpel and all Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel Ordinances, as Preaching, Baptiſme, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are to ſuch worldly men I ſpeak of, no better then fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and weakneſſe, and therefore as poore and weake things, are deſpiſed by them and caſt away, No man need ſeeke farre for reaſons, why theſe things ſhould have that Notion and Character in the ſpirits and reaſonings of men not ſubjected to the ſpirit.</p>
            <p>Certainely becauſe things indeed ſpirituall ſuite with none of their principles, they have nothing they can take their meaſure by; a man that would judge of any thing, judges by ſome principles within him: But then againe, becauſe there is a meanes and low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in them, which is abominable to carnall wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, as the waſhing of <hi>Naaman</hi> the Leper in <hi>Jor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan:</hi> As alſo becauſe they can ſee no ſuitableneſſe and correſpondence betwene the meanes and the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, as <hi>Epicurus</hi> diſputes againſt the making of the World, where (ſayes he) were the Engines, the Lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, what deviſes to rayſe ſuch a mighty building?</p>
            <p>But upon what ever ground this may bee, which I purpoſe not here to inlarge in; no man that conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:117372:23"/>
the premiſes will deny me this, That to be ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalized and offended at the Goſpel, Chriſt crucified, and the Ordinances of Preaching, Baptiſme, the Lords Supper (for they hold of the ſame weakneſſe, hold out a dying ſuffering Chriſt) is a ſigne of a car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, worldly heart.</p>
            <p>But here I muſt ſtand the Butt of ſome Objections which I ſhall be ſure to meet withall, and be ingaged to anſwer certaine demands, which theſe pretended ſpiritualiſts will be ſure to make to me: In the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer and conſideration of which, that truth which I contend for, will, I hope, be made manifeſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>1</label> Firſt, therefore it will be ſayd, thoſe men that are   prejudiced againſt Ordinances, are not againſt a cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that ſuch ſeeme to be the moſt ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all of any other.</p>
            <p>For the firſt, they muſt needs be prejudic'd as well againſt a crucified Chriſt, for it is no more weake and fooliſh to be baptized in water, or breake bread, according to the inſtitution; then it is to beleeue in a Saviour hanged or crucified.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>De facto,</hi> they are ſo, and make the cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifixion of Chriſt, a kind of figurative allegoricall thing, which was to make ſuch a repreſentation of Gods mind to us, and then to end, not a thing indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and remaining, they make a kind of notionall thing, of all the birth, life, ſuffering, reſurrection, and ſeſſion in Heaven of Chriſt a thing for weake men, and weake times.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>2</label> Secondly, For their ſeeming to be moſt ſpiritual. </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> By way of anſwer to that, I would conſider that the Apoſtle in the ſecond of the <hi>Colloſsians,</hi> ſeemes to
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:117372:24"/>
forewarne thoſe to whom he writes, of two ſorts of errings; the one, about antiquated formes of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Jewiſh ceremonies, which men naturally ſuperſtitious, and of a more groſſe and dull ſpirit are apt to bee deluded by; this hee mentions, Verſe 16. <hi>Let no man therefore judge you in meat and drinke, or in reſpect of an holy day, or of the new Moone, &amp;c. Which are but the ſhadow of things to come, but the body is of Chriſt.</hi> Thoſe things which were but ſhadows, and typicall, are vaniſht at the appearing of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and ſubſtance: The other was about ſuch decep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and deluſions as men of more rayſed and notio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſpirits were in danger of; of thoſe hee ſpeakes, Ver. 8. <hi>Take heed leaſt any man ſpoyle you, through Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy and vaine deceit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There ſeemes to have been in thoſe dayes, as there are in theſe, certaine ſpirits, who not contented with the meanneſſe and lowneſſe of the Doctrine of Chriſt crucifyed, with ſuch Ordinances and adminiſtrations as the ſpirit of God judged proper for the exhibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and making good to us ſuch a Doctrine, would frame a kind of Philoſophicall rationall Divinity, ſavouring rather the ſpirit of <hi>Plato,</hi> and <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> then of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and which being full of uncouth and unuſuall expreſſions, made the people admire what they underſtood not, and cauſed that to paſſe for ſpirituall (though it were but vaine deceit) which ſeemed moſt remote from the common and uſuall, though the trueſt and righteſt apprehenſion. I affirme therefore, that it is but a carnall ſpiritualli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which theſe men have, and hold out; ſuch as Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers ſubtelizing ſpirituall things with worldly diſtinctions, and notions, not holding the head, and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:117372:24"/>
indeed covering their carnall apprehenſions under the name of ſpirituall; for that which a <hi>Socinian</hi> calls plainely and more honeſtly, <hi>Humana ratio,</hi> that they call the ſpirit, covering it with a fairer name, but both the one and the other, are tranſgreſſours a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like; both philoſophating as wildly the one, as the other, about ſpirituall things, ſaving that theſe lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter are worſe, keeping neither to the forme of whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome words that the Scripture gives us, nor to prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of right reaſon, having this for an unanſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able cloake when ever they are driven to a wall, that that is dictated to them by the ſpirit. And I doubt not but that the evill and uncleane ſpirit is fertile of notions and ſupplyes, by his ſuggeſtions, the irratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nality of their opinions and practices.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> If you aske now why God ordained ſuch <hi>mediums</hi> as theſe,  things ſo unſuitable and unproportionable to the reaſon and wiſedome of men.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> I anſwer, <hi>That no fleſh ſhould glory in his preſence,</hi>  1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.29. Wherefore would God deſtroy <hi>Jericho</hi> by the blowing of Rams-hornes, <hi>Joſhua</hi> 6. If all the men of Warre had taken it by an ordinary ſiege, they would have had the glory, and God would have loſt his; but when the walls of a mighty City ſhall fall downe flat before the blowing of Rams-hornes, and a little inſtituted ceremony of incompaſſing it in ſuch a manner, ſo many dayes, God alone had the glory, and no fleſh could glory in his preſence, upon the ſame account in this great worke of ſalvation (wherein if in any he would intirely have the praiſe, and is eſpecially jealous leaſt his glory ſhould be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to another) <hi>God hath choſen fooliſh things, and baſe things, and weake things, and things which are deſpiſed,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:117372:25"/>
and things which are not, to bring to nought things that are,</hi> Verſe 27, 28, 29. Such as Chriſt crucified is, and all the ſeeming fooliſh, weake, and low Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of Chriſt, as Preaching, Aſſembling, Church-fellowſhip, Baptiſme, breaking of bread, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſecondly, God doth this becauſe we are poore, low, and fooliſh creatures, and God would have us by ſuch things, remembred of it continually. Our bodies are one halfe of us, our ſoules and bodies make but one perſon; our bodies as well as our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, are the temples of the holy Ghoſt, and yet what pityfull, languiſhing, needy pieces are they; how do they ſubſiſt in a continuall ſucceſſion of fillings and emptyings, how are they wound up by meate and drinke, and lye fallow by reſt; ſo meane are they, as the Apoſtle knowes no Epithite more proportion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to them, then that of <hi>Our vile bodies;</hi> ſo are our ſpirits, weake and fooliſh things, ſuch as if they were let alone, to runne to the utmoſt bounds of their owne ſpeculations, would runne out to the greateſt vanities and extravagancies, would be vaine in their reaſonings, and profeſſing wiſedome, would become fooles; therefore like fooles and children, God deales with us: And why doe we not pretend as well that our bodyes ſhould live angelicall lives, without the aydes of food and raiment, as that our ſoules ſhould not need ſuch Ordinances, and Inſtitutions, for there is the like reaſon of both, and when our bodies ſhall not need thoſe aydes, but be as the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, our ſpirits ſhall alſo bee freed from any ſuch tracts or formes of worſhip, as for the preſent God hath made our portion and bleſſing. Though ſome I heare (wiſely in that making the notion go round)
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:117372:25"/>
ſay they are in a glorified ſtate alſo, in reſpect of the body, and that they doe but ſeeme to eate or drinke, or doe any other actions of life.</p>
            <p>If you aske then, what difference is betweene us and the Jewes, who were under <hi>Moſes,</hi> who had ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies and mediate Ordinances.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, Very much, as much as betweene open-facedneſſe, and vailing, betweene ſeeing in a Picture and ſeeing in a glaſſe; <hi>Quod videtur in ſpeculo non eſt Image,</hi> 'tis the thing it ſelfe, not the picture or image of it; and therefore the Apoſtle, ſpeaking of the difference betweene the <hi>Jewes</hi> and <hi>Chriſtians: The vayle</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is over their hearts, but we all with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen face behold as in a Glaſſe the glory of the Lord,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.18. But the ſame Apoſtle ſpeaking of our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſtate, with the times that are to come, ſayes, <hi>That we ſee as a childe, and underſtand as a childe, and that we ſee through a glaſſe and in a riddle, but then face to face;</hi> and the ſeeing on this manner is to continue till <hi>Prophecy ſhall fayle and tongues ſhall ceaſe and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge ſhall vaniſh away:</hi> I thinke, in this life there is no body that will deny that there is uſe of ability in tongues, of the gifts of ſcience or knowledge, and propheſie, which are of great uſe to the people of God, for the begetting them to the faith, and for their building up as long as is uſe of faith or hope, but when we come <hi>to live by ſight and not by faith, to be abſent from the body, and preſent with the Lord,</hi> 3 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.7. Then, and not before, tongues, propheſies, faith, and hope, ſhall ceaſe together; then <hi>wee ſhall know as we are knowne and not in part, and ſhall ſee no longer through a glaſſe, darkly, but face to face,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. That is, all thoſe eclipſing <hi>mediums,</hi> which are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:117372:26"/>
and neceſſary to this ſtate whilſt we are in the body, and in this earthly Tabernacle ſhall vaniſh to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and there will be a ſeeing and converſe with God, more rayſed, and more divine, then wee can now conceive of: In a word, every body will eaſily, I conceive, diſcerne the vaſt difference of theſe Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, from thoſe of old, by conſidering the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of the two Covenants, and the glory of the Goſpell, from what was that of the Law; as for Propheſie or Preaching, common to us, with the <hi>Jewes,</hi> it holds out the whole mind of God in Chriſt, the great myſtery of godlineſſe, God manifeſted in the fleſh, gives us that in hiſtory and accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which the <hi>Jewes</hi> that lived under another Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant had but darkly in predictions and types, they but a <hi>ſhadow and not the image, Heb.</hi> 10. Now we ſee the things have more then the image, as I ſayd, that which is ſeene in a glaſſe is not the image; 'tis the thing, and as this is true of propheſying or preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſo there will be found to be the ſame reaſon of other adminiſtrations, thoſe wee call Sacraments, Baptiſme, and breaking of bread, which is the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of the ſame Goſpell to us, by the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation of other ſenſes; therefore theſe Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces have the ſame advantage over the Sacraments of the Law, that the Goſpell it ſelfe hath over the Law, confirmes to our faith by the mediation of other ſenſes all the riches and glory of the Goſpell, and what ever revelation the ſpirit of God makes to us therein, ſcales to us that in hiſtory, and performed, which was darkly before repreſented in types, and God having made himſelfe viſible now at laſt in his Sonne, makes his Son and all his beauties and glories
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:117372:26"/>
viſible to us in his Ordinances, the holy Ghoſt ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to our ſenſes, by the mediation of words, or things, or ſignes of the ſame efficacy, with words ſet apart for that purpoſe, the great myſtery of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell. But laſtly, and particularly to thoſe two Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of Baptiſme and breaking of bread (which beſides other things, holds forth to us directly and immediately the death and ſufferings of Chriſt) why may it not be thought that our Lord hath parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly inſtituted theſe to keepe freſh to us for our comfort and his honour, that great love wherewith he loved us when hee gave himſelfe for us to death, which the Scripture magnifies and values ſo much as to give it for the higheſt inſtance of the love of God the Father; <hi>God ſo loved the World that he gave his one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly begotten Sonne,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 3. and alſo of the greateſt and higheſt engagement of our love to him. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.14. <hi>The love of Chriſt conſtraineth us:</hi> Now this which ſpeakes Gods love ſo much, and ingages ours ſo fully, and which in reſpect of the condition of our ſtate in this life is of ſo great concernment, God would have kept freſh to us, by moſt viſible and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible demonſtrations, and the rather to prevent and meet with the ingratitude of unworthy men, who after they have ſerved their turne of him, fling away Chriſt crucified, as an element as beggerly as any of thoſe Ordinances which repreſent it, and under I know not what vanity or pride of notion, caſt that behind their backs, which <hi>Paul</hi> in his preaching de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired eſpecially to know and manifeſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.2. Thus much for what I thought to ſay to this head concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the difference betweene us and the <hi>Jewes</hi> in our formes of worſhip and miniſtration.</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:117372:27"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> But if any ſhall bee yet unſatisfied with this, as pretending after a more ſpirituall converſe with God then is ſuitable to ſuch Ordinances of preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Baptiſme, Church fellowſhippe, breaking of bread, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>1</label> I anſwer firſt, That for ſome part of theſe, to wit, Prophecy, or Preaching, neither God, nor the Devil, will eaſily part with that under any notion whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; not God, becauſe by the fooliſhneſſe of preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hee ſaves them that beleeve, it is a mighty Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance in his hands for the converting and building up his in the faith and knowledge of him; nor the Devill, what ever in a kind of gallantry he or ſuch as are acted by him may pretend to, for he would want the moſt proper, and naturall, and eaſie <hi>medium</hi> to diffuſe and propagate his lyes; and therefore when I have heard of ſome who having propheſied noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious lyes in the name of the Lord, have by the ſame ſpirit of lying fayned themſelves in the ſtate of the reſurrection, and that therefore they were to pray and preach no more; I alwayes ſayd, before the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent proved it true, that for the buſineſſe of preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing I would undertake they ſhould not long refraine that, what ever became of other things, for as much as the Devill would not long looſe that mighty en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine of diffuſing his principles, and accordingly theſe perſons have beene ſince the moſt conſtant and diligent Preachers, and the Devill hath not beene wanting to his uſuall methods of transforming him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe into an Angell of light, and mingling abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble lyes with ſeeming rayſed, and high, and ſpirituall expreſſions, that the one may be ſet of, and take bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by the ayde and aſſiſtance of the other.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:117372:27"/>Then if propheſying, or preaching, or conference, which are of the ſame nature wil be allowed by theſe men that are ſcandalized at the fooliſhneſſe of Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances; why not Baptiſme, breaking of bread, and the reſt, which are no more fooliſh, nor no more carnall then the other; for cannot the holy ſpirit ſpeake as ſpiritually and as effectually by theſe Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roglyphick's of its inſtitution, as by the words and reaſonings of any man? Cannot it tell you the love of the great God, the merits of the death of Chriſt, what conformity and aſſimilation God expects from you to your head, with all the reſt of thoſe things, wherein theſe Ordinances inſtruct you, as well as by the words or reaſonings of any man, which unleſſe the ſpirit informe and inliven it, is as dull and improper to convey ſpirituall things to us, and in it ſelfe as low and carnall as any other <hi>medium</hi> you can imagine?</p>
            <p>This being granted, as it cannot be denied, they who will admit of propheſying or preaching or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference which goe all under one head, cannot deny any of the reſt, Church-fellowſhip, Church-aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, Baptiſme, breaking of bread, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and fit <hi>mediums</hi> for Gods convaying himſelfe to us in any piece of ſpirituall knowledge or manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for ſince it is the holy ſpirit that muſt doe all that is done in us, and upon us, for good, the holy ſpirit hath and can make as good uſe of theſe <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diums</hi> and preach to us upon that text as well as upon the word, or expreſſions, or reaſonings of any man whatſoever, and it is as proper and ſuitable to that bleſſed ſpirit to ſpeake to us by things, as by words, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Words in themſelves and in their letter are
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:117372:28"/>
as carnall and unfit for our ſpirituall edification, as any thing you can imagine.</p>
            <p>This anſwer therefore is a <hi>Pari,</hi> if you will allow of preaching or conferences (which as I ſaid none will be found to denie long) there will be no good reaſon to reprobate or reject Baptiſme, breaking of bread, Church-fellowſhip, or the reſt, as things in their nature improper and unſpirituall; for whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver reaſon comes from inſtitution we ſhall examine that afterwards.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>2</label> But then ſecondly, for thoſe who would lay aſide theſe <hi>mediums</hi> as things more carnall and bodily then befits their ſtate (whether wilfully or ignorantly they deceive themſelves and others) I would intreat them to conſider how they come to apprehend any things ſpirituall, or whether whilſt they are in the body, whilſt their ſoules live in theſe houſes of clay, they can reaſon, underſtand (by which ſpirituall impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions are conveyed) without the ayde and aſſiſtance of the body: For though God hath this prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence effectually to inlighten the underſtanding, and determine the will in reſpect of the event, which no creature, man, or Angell, can doe; yet the way by which he accommodates himſelfe to us in the doing of theſe things is ſtill <hi>human<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> more,</hi> and after the rate and proportion of our weakneſſes, as wee are able and fitted to receive things being in the body, and in this mixt, lame, and imperfect ſtate in which wee are, when Gods ſpeaks to us by men or things, it is alwaies by the mediation of our externall ſenſes, but when hee goes another way to worke, it is not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the body, but by the mediation of phantaſmes either formerly received, or newly injected (which
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:117372:28"/>
God can doe, though perhaps neither men nor An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels can) he repreſents objects to our underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and wills, which take and move us as it peaſeth him to give the bleſſing; ſo as you cannot contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate nor meditate, nor reaſon, nor thinke of God, without the aſſiſtance and uſe of the body, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive impreſſions from him upon your underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and will, and affections, but by the ſame way. It is therefore groſſe ignorance in men, as it is in the moſt (aſſiſted and improved by pride) or wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which makes them ſubject to theſe miſtakes to judge that converſe with God unholy and unſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall which is adminiſtred to us by the mediation of Ordinances, which are outward and ſubjected to our ſenſes.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>3</label> But then thirdly, I would have theſe men conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the true nature and reaſon of this word <hi>ſpirituall,</hi>  as it ſtands in order to the diſcourſe wee have in hand.</p>
            <p>The notion of ſpirituall lies not in this, that one is more raiſed and improved in parts then another, as when the <hi>French</hi> ſay, <hi>C'eſt vn homme bien ſpirituel,</hi> they meane a man of good parts, or of a raiſed ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: Though I very much feare that this goes farre for ſpirituall with many, and a great deale of that language and converſe which is called ſpirituall, is nothing but the expreſſions of men of a more raiſed reaſon, or exoticke and extravagant fancy, which becauſe the language is unuſual goes amongſt a great many ignorant and well meaning men for ſpirituall, as appeares by their inordinate affecting certaine preachings and writings, which a ſober, holy, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſpirituall man would looke upon with other
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:117372:29"/>
eyes. Wherein the lucke is, that ſuch kind of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors are beſt and moſt readily underſtood, by thoſe who as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>are ever learning and never able to come to the knowledge of the truth,</hi> which ſuites very happily with ſuch Teachers, who as the ſame Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Know neither what they ſay, nor wherof they affirme.</hi> Spiritualneſſe therefore lies not in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing or affecting ſuch Preachers, or Authors, or wayes as come under a ſhew of raiſed or improved reaſon or fancy.</p>
            <p>Nor doth it lye in this, that ſuch waies or wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip are more proportionable or more ſuitable to the guiſe and faſhion of the next, or a more raiſed ſtate: If any one could by the ſpirit of propheſie or divine revelation, peepe into another World, and ſee what the converſe of that ſhall be, ſuch a ſearch would be of excellent uſe to us as it was to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets of old, <hi>who inquired and ſearched diligently after the times that were to come,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10. But would be no warrant to alter or change from the way of life, or worſhip of the preſent ſtate; for then <hi>Jeroboam</hi> had hit it, though not in his end perhaps, yet in the thing, who by altering the times and places of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip did but anticipate Goſpell practice, when it ſhould be lawfull every where and at all times and ſeaſons to offer up ſacrifices acceptable and agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to God. Then alſo it had beene more ſpirituall in the laſt ſtate, or times of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> to ſignifie Chriſts death by breaking of bread, then by ſlaying of Oxen, or by worſhipping God without Preiſtly adornments and ceremonies, rather then with them. Some of the Prophets, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> particularly, and <hi>David</hi> ſaw farre into the way of that ſtate that
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:117372:29"/>
was then to come, yet neither did the one nor the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther nor any of the holy Prophets diſſwade from the practice of the ceremonies or ordinances of that time, though ſuch as the Apoſtle ſince hath called beggarly rudiments, but incouraged and exhorted ſtill to the conſtant perſevering in them, onely blam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them when they were alone without holineſſe of life and converſation, and faith in God, which they all tended to and taught, who of all the Prophets underſtood the way of a ſpirituall converſe more then <hi>David,</hi> as appeares by his frequent calling upon the ſpirit, bemoaning the abſenſe of glorying in the enjoyment of it, and yet this excellent and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall <hi>David</hi> thought it not a carnall and unſpirituall thing to converſe with God in the Ordinances of that ſtate wherein he lived, though he ſaw ſo clearly and happily into another and better, but longed after the ceremonious worſhip of thoſe times, and envied even the condition of the Sparrowes that found a reſting in Gods houſe, and by Gods Altar, from which he was excluded.</p>
            <p>And if we conſider it particularly, how abſurd would ſuch a thing be, the wiſe God hath fitted the liquour to the veſſell, our way of converſe with him in things ſpirituall according to our preſent recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive faculty, how ridiculous would it be to ſuite the garment of a man to a childs body, or becauſe a child hath a principle in him that is rationall, to labour in that uncapable age to improve that principle by ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall diſcourſes and diſcipline: So and much more abſurd and vaine is it to ſuite and proportion the converſe of a future and more raiſed ſtate to the lowneſſe and incapacity of a former and more weake
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:117372:30"/>
and childiſh one; yet nothing is more frequently done by theſe men wee have beene ſpeaking of, by which meanes it fals out that being wholy unfit for the converſe of a more excellent and future ſtate, and neglecting and ſleighting that way of converſe which God hath made their portion for the preſent, they looſe the bleſſing of their preſent ſtate, and all thoſe influences which God conveyes to us, by <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diums</hi> of his owne fitting, and in ſtead of increaſing in light which they ſo much pretend to, <hi>they grow vaine in their imaginations, and have their fooliſh hearts darkened</hi> (as their abominable and curſed opinion evidently makes appeare) <hi>by that Prince of darkneſſe who transformes himſelfe into an Angell of light.</hi> So that to conclude, it is the word of inſtitution for the preſent ſtate in which we live, that gives the notion of ſpiritualneſſe to Ordinances, and actions, and neither the vanity of our reaſonings, nor a pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or reall ſight into the ſtate of thoſe times that are to come.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Coroll. </seg>
               </label> To all this, and as a Corollary to this diſcourſe, I would adde this, That never any ſtate or way of worſhip was changed without a very great viſibility and notoriety to thoſe whom it concerned. When by the hands of <hi>Moſes</hi> there was but a graduall change, and a greater formalizing of the worſhip of the ſame Covenant; no man will denie me, but that it was by the appointment of God made ſo viſible and ſo publike, as there was nothing left of obſcuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie or doubtfulneſſe in it: <hi>Moſes</hi> the Miniſter of ſo great a change, was a man who had his Letters of cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence from Heaven, written in the moſt viſible Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters; a man that wrought ordinarily, many and
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:117372:30"/>
great miracles, that was owned by God by many hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly apparitions: and yet beſides all this, when the rule of life and worſhip was given, <hi>God himſelfe tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked to them from Heaven,</hi> as he ſayes, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.22. and after the greateſt preparation of the people for receiving thoſe heavenly Oracles, that there might be no doubt but that they were from God; <hi>Mount Sinai</hi> (whither the people aſſembled) <hi>was altogether in a ſmoake, becauſe the Lord deſcended upon it in fire, and the ſmoake thereof aſcended as the ſmoake of a Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace, and the whole mount quaked greatly, and when the voyce of the Trumpet ſounded long and waxed lowder and lowder, God anſwered him by a voyce,</hi> Verſe 18, 19. Of which voice of God the people were ſo aſſured, <hi>As they beſought Moſes that he would ſpeake with them, and that God might not ſpeake with them leaſt they dye, Exod.</hi> 20.19. So as though afterwards they proved a ſtiff-necked people, <hi>who having received the Law by the diſpoſition of Angells did not keepe it, Acts</hi> 7.51, 53. Yet no man could pretend their ignorance of the mind of God, or that the forme appointed to them by <hi>Moſes</hi> was not of Divine inſtitution and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.</p>
            <p>In like manner when thoſe Ceremonies and that way of worſhip was to ceaſe, and a new and a very different adminiſtration both of Doctrine and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip was to be in the World, the wiſedome of God judged it meet (as before) to give the World a good account of it, that no man might juſtly pretend ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance in a thing of that great moment and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment; and although the World (the <hi>Jewes</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially to whom the firſt addreſſes were made) were particularly prepared for it by a long ſeries
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:117372:31"/>
and conſent of propheſies which told them of very famous and notable changes, which had formed their ſpirits to a ſteady and earneſt expectation of them, yet God intending to make a greater change in the World then was before, uſed a greater Miniſter then <hi>Moſes,</hi> having therefore formerly contented himſelfe to ſpeake by the Prophets, <hi>He ſpake unto us now by his Sonne, whom he appointed heyre of all things, and by whom he made the World;</hi> and that we might be obliged to heare him, and to receive from his mouth this new Series of Doctrine and Ceremonies which have been the rule of our Faith and Worſhip ever ſince, it pleaſed God <hi>to declare this Sonne of God with power according to the ſpirit of holineſſe by the reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the dead;</hi> and to anoynt others (according to their meaſure) with the ſame ſpirit of holineſſe which ſhould be under Miniſters, to this great Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd of our ſoules, and which by moſt reall and mighty ſignes and miracles ſhould confirme that Doctrine, and thoſe inſtitutions of Worſhip which he brought from Heaven and gave unto the World. So as this change was moſt viſible to all, manifeſted not onely to the reaſon and faith of men, but to their very ſenſes, ſo as no man could pretend ignorance, or reaſon of doubting, ſo as the fault muſt reſt in their will, <hi>they would not come to him that they might have life, and they loved darkneſſe rather then light, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their deeds were evill.</hi> Yea, our Lord appeales to his workes and miracles, and ſayes, that if he had not done, <hi>amongſt them the workes that never any man did, they had beene without ſinne, but now they had no cloake nor no excuſe:</hi> Thus it hath pleaſed God to deale with us when ever he hath given a rule of Faith
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:117372:31"/>
or worſhip, or hath ſhaken and removed old forms of adminiſtration (which were the tracts and wayes in which he hath met his people, and communicated of himſelfe to them) he hath ever given ſuch viſible and ſenſible teſtimonies of theſe things to the World, as was fit to give a generall and full ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, that ſuch was undoubtedly the pleaſure and will of God in things of ſo great moment and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment.</p>
            <p>Now that Chriſtians in the dayes of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and ſince to theſe very times have been poſſeſſed of certaine Ordinances and formes of worſhip, ſuch as Preaching, Conference, Baptiſme, breaking of bread, and to comprehend all theſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der one head, Church-fellowſhip, in all its admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations of gifts and offices (though with much variation in the way &amp; reaſon of adminiſtring theſe things) I thinke no body will deny.</p>
            <p>But where (in the name of God I aske it) are thoſe Divine Warrants which formerly have not been wanting to theſe caſes made manifeſt and viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to us, as formerly by mighty miracles, by the voyce of God, or the Sonne of God from Heaven (as formerly ſtill) which ſhould deſtroy that was built, and make ſuch changes our duty, which elſe without them would be the higheſt and greateſt Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge.</p>
            <p>I appeale to God and man, whether any ſuch things be or no; nay I dare be bold to ſay it in the Name of God, to all holy and rationall men, that there hath no ſuch thing been, and that what ever hath been held out for any ſuch mighty change and alteration for the preſent hath been nothing but an
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:117372:32"/>
abſurd and ridiculous allegorizing, of certaine paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages of Scripture, which very Scripture, theſe men that would deſtroy Ordinances, looke upon gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, with as ill an eye as they doe on any of the reſt of theſe formes, as they call them, but find good to make uſe of it now and then, for the more aſſured deceiving of themſelves and others: I ſay there ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been no ſuch mighty and viſible and authentick warrant for this change as becomes ſo great a buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and as formerly God hath been uſed to give in things of this nature, nor nothing like it, nor no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all, but the bold vanity and ſpeculation of ſome men which would intrude their reaſonings and revelations as good Goſpel upon the world; I hope we ſhall learne to be ſober, <hi>Not to be wiſe above what is written,</hi> nor to thinke that God hath altered or quitted all his methods in matters of ſo great mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and concernment to the World, becauſe it is ſuitable and agreeable to the fancies of a few men, the principall and moſt leading of which have been ſufficiently deceived to the view of all men in thoſe things wherein they have moſt avowedly and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently intereſted the name and authority of God himſelfe, and of whom I will be bold to ſay, that the beſt and ingenious excuſe their owne friends and followers can make for them is, that they are in ſome degree of madneſſe and diſtraction.</p>
            <p>This I would ſpare to affirme, but that it is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriouſly knowne, and it is fit alſo that the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God ſhould be knowne, and that the hand of God is eminently out againſt thoſe who fear not the curſe of <hi>adding to, or taking away,</hi> and either out of the vanity of their owne reaſonings, or from Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolicall
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:117372:32"/>
inſpirations are bold with him in things of ſo great concernment as are the utter racing and taking away of Goſpell Ordinances, and Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>Having ſayd what I intended about the nature of Ordinances in generall, and the reaſon of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance, I ſhall labour now more particularly to vindicate from that contempt and ſcorne which is put upon it by ſome men, the Ordinance of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, not onely to reſcue that Inſtitution from the violence that is offered to it, but by an illuſtrious inſtance in one of the ſame kind with the reſt, and one at this time more oppoſed and undermined then any, to give a further account and ſhew more cauſe for the abiding and continuing with us of all the reſt.</p>
            <p>There hath been a great and much agitated contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie betweene the Papiſts and thoſe of the reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Religion concerning the identity and efficacy of <hi>Johns</hi> Baptiſme (as it is called) compared with Chriſt; The Papiſts thundering Anathemaes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them who ſhall affirme the Baptiſme of <hi>John</hi> to have the ſame vertue and power with that of Chriſts: Thoſe of the reformed Religion on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide are generally of opinion, that the Miniſtry of <hi>John</hi> was the the ſame that was after delega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Apoſtles, and that the Baptiſme of <hi>John</hi> was the ſame which was adminiſtred after by the Diſciples and Apoſtles of our Lord, and which by the command of Chriſt was to be propagated into all the World, and all Nations to be Baptized with it.</p>
            <p>This controverſie though in the tearmes of it, it
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:117372:33"/>
remaines much the ſame, yet in ſenſe and meaning it is exceedingly changed by ſome men of this genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, who would have us beleeve that there is no uſe of Water in the Baptiſme of Chriſt (that belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing onely to <hi>Johns</hi> Miniſtry, the laſt terme of which was the Aſcention of Chriſt) but that Chriſts Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme and the rule and Inſtitution of it, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.29. <hi>Goe teach all Nations, baptizing them, &amp;c.</hi> is not to plung and dip them in cold Water, as <hi>John</hi> did his Diſciples, <hi>But baptize them or dip them into the Name of God the Father, Sonne, and Spirit;</hi> that is (to uſe their owne words) by the Miniſtry which ſhall be of the Spirit, and not of the Letter, <hi>You ſhall Baptize them, or dip them, or intereſt them into the Name of God, who is the Father, Sonne, and Spirit, or ſprinkle his Name upon them, that they may be holy, juſt, true, mercifull, righteous, good, &amp;c.</hi> The drift of all is (as they affirme diſtinctly) to exclude Water Baptiſme, in lieu of which as a thing contradiſtinct, they would bring you in Spirit Baptiſme.</p>
            <p>To make this good, they draw moſt of their beſt weapons out of the Popiſh Quiver, in the diſputes betweene us and them, of the difference of <hi>Johns</hi> Baptiſme from that of Chriſts, though they manage them to a quite other purpoſe then they meant them, for we and they differ about the efficacy of Baptiſme by Water; they (the Papiſts) affirming that Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme doth <hi>ex opere operato,</hi> conferre grace; that is, by the force and vertue of its adminiſtration with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any reſpect to the foregoing Faith and Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance in the party baptized, in which reſpect they preferre it to the Baptiſme of <hi>John</hi> adminiſtred alſo by Water; but theſe would have us beleeve that
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:117372:33"/>
there is no ſuch thing remaining to Chriſtians as Baptiſme by water: When therefore I ſay they have helped themſelves by theſe borrowed arguments to ſhew that the baptiſme of Chriſt and that of <hi>John</hi> are two things, and abuſed the Popiſh arguments to their owne ends, then with many a ſpecious flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh they acquaint you with the excellency of ſpirit Baptiſme above water Baptiſme, wherein as in a Theame very eaſie they make a great flouriſh, and ſhew us (forſooth) how much the efficacy of the ſpirit is more then water, which (for honour ſake no doubt) ever and anon they call cold water, and ſo at length conclude with that which all the premiſes drive at, that all outward and carnall and earthly things are put to an end (in which number all out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward adminiſtrations are contained) by the inward ſpirituall and heavenly things of a better and ſecond teſtament. In which how little ſincerely and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully they deale with holy Ordinances, and the great Maſter and Inſtitutor of them, <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing their Apocryphall novelties upon the people under the ſpecious title of a more rayſed and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall adminiſtration, as I have in part ſhewed alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy more generally in the preceding diſcourſe, ſo I ſhall endeavour more particularly in the vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Ordinance of Baptiſme to make ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt.</p>
            <p>For my owne part, I have thought that the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of <hi>Johns</hi> and <hi>Chriſts</hi> Baptiſme was not very conſiderable, for we, by the acknowledgment of all, injoying Chriſts baptiſme, it was of leſſe moment to know what the difference of the two Baptiſmes were if there were any.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:117372:34"/>But as it comes ſtated to us by new hands (and it is the particular credit of errour that it is new) there is nothing more conſiderable, ſince by vertue of that diſtinction of <hi>Johns</hi> and <hi>Chriſts</hi> Baptiſme, they would utterly take away the Ordinance of Baptiſme it ſelfe, and by a like reaſon all the reſt, which with ſo much comfort and edification the Saints of God have knowne how to uſe as pledges of love, and paths and tracts of Communion with God in Jeſus Chriſt, without adoreing them or putting them in Gods place; though I confeſſe according to what our corruption is, that is not without danger, but it is the part of good and wiſe men to reform errour without overthrowing foundations; on the other ſide, folly ever reſts in the extremities to which the Devill drives it.</p>
            <p>That there is a Goſpell, New Teſtament, Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, that theſe men will grant, and that it is par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly held out in theſe places, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19, 20. and <hi>Marke</hi> 16.15, 16. The words of <hi>Matthew</hi> are <hi>Goe teach all Nations, baptizing them in the Name of the Father, the Sonne, and holy Ghoſt, teaching them to obſerve all things whatſoever I have commanded you, and ſo I am with you unto the end of the World.</hi> To ſay here that Chriſt might mean baptiſme by water, of which ceremony there ſhould be an end within a certaine time, is to contradict the expreſſe words of the Scripture, that ſayes he will be with them in theſe things unto the end of the World, and they may with as good reaſon prefix a time to the ending of Faith and Hope, or any Chriſtian grace or Ordinance according to their owne fancies, or pleaſures, or to Preaching alſo, ſince Preaching and Baptiſme are here put together.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:117372:34"/>But ſome would Philoſophate more ſubtlely and tell you, that by baptizing here, is not meant dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping or plunging in water, in the Name of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But <hi>to Baptize them, or dip them, or intereſt them into the Name of God, or ſprinkling his Name up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, that they may be holy, juſt, mercifull, righteous, good.</hi> But beſides that this is boldly affirmed, how ridiculous and abſurd it is, you will eaſily ſee; bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, becauſe in a thing of this moment, upon a ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e affirmation, without any proofe, they goe againſt what hath been the ſenſe of all ages, and of all men if you will judge of their ſenſe as we muſt needs doe by their preachings and by their practice; but ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous I ſay alſo, and abſurd it is. The words are, wee know, <hi>Goe teach all Nations,</hi> or diſciple them, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and then <hi>Baptize them,</hi> that is, firſt make them Diſciples, firſt make them beleevers, and then baptize them; therefore in <hi>Marke,</hi> the place before quoted, <hi>Hee that beleeves and is baptized, ſhall bee ſaved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>According to this word of Inſtitution and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, yee have exactly the Apoſtolicall practice (and this I dare affirme, there can be no better way of finding out the nature of any Ordinance then by comparing the practice with the Inſtitution.) The practice you will find in ſeverall places, particularly, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.34, 35. When <hi>Philip</hi> had Preacht to the Eunuch, <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and the Ordinance of Baptiſme, as it appeares, becauſe the Eunuch demands it inſtantly upon the ſight of water, <hi>Philip</hi> tells him the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Baptiſme, which was beleeving in Chriſt with all his heart, which when the Eunuch affirmes he did, <hi>Philip,</hi> according to the command of our Lord,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:117372:35"/>
went downe into the water with him, and baptized him: Where you have the inſtitution run parallell with the practice as exactly as is poſſible.</p>
            <p>I ſhall name but one place more amongſt many, which is that of the 10 of the <hi>Acts,</hi> where, after that <hi>Peter</hi> had Preached largely to <hi>Cornelius</hi> and his Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the Lord Jeſus, and the great things of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell through him, and that their Faith which was the condition of Baptiſme, was gloriouſly manifeſted by the powring down of the holy Ghoſt upon them, <hi>Peter</hi> puts them preſently upon baptiſme, as the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond piece of his Commiſſion, which was to bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize thoſe which by his Preaching were made Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and did beleeve, and therefore commanded them to be baptized in water.</p>
            <p>Thus you have the rule verifyed in the practice, and there is no Comment ſo good upon the rule or precept, as Apoſtolicall practice.</p>
            <p>I have ſayd before, that this forced interpretation was bold, as you may ſee it further evidently, by what hath been laſt ſayd in the exact correſponden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy betweene the rule and practice; but you will ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily ſee it alſo fooliſh, for I beſeech you what is that which denominates any man holy, juſt, and good, but beleeving in God through Chriſt? And what is it to be a Diſciple, or to be a Chriſtian, but to be all that? He that beleeveth, and is made a Diſciple, <hi>is baptized or intereſted,</hi> as they call it, <hi>into the Name of God and is made holy, juſt, true, righteous, mercifull, good,</hi> which is all that they underſtand by Baptiſme ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in theſe places; then if beleeving, or being made a Diſciple, be all that, that interpretation which they would inforce upon theſe places is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:117372:35"/>
but a loathſome and abſurd tautology, thus; indoctrinate, teach or Diſciple all Nations; that is, make them holy, juſt, righteous, good, mercifull, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> intereſt them in God (for that no queſtion they are when they are made Diſciples and beleeve) and then baptize them; that is, make them holy, juſt, righteous, good, intereſt them in God; or as it is <hi>Mark, Chap.</hi> 16. <hi>verſ.</hi> 15, 16. <hi>Preach the Goſpell to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Creature, he that beleeveth,</hi> that is, is intereſted in God, is made holy, juſt, good, mercifull, <hi>&amp;c. And is baptized;</hi> that is, is intereſted in God, is made ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, juſt, good, mercifull, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſhall be ſaved. What a monſtrous and abſurd thing is this new expoſition to make the holy Scriptures ſpeake not onely any thing to the gingle of our owne fancies, but even the moſt abominable and loathſome tautologies and Nonſence.</p>
            <p>Things thus ſtated, I am not ſolicitous about that queſtion concerning <hi>Johns</hi> baptiſme, whether in all reſpects it be the ſame with that, concerning which Chriſt Commiſſioned his Diſciples, and was uſed by the Apoſtles after the Aſcenſion of our Lord; that is, whether it were generally of that efficacy and vertue before the Aſcenſion of Chriſt, as after; which is the queſtion as it lyes betweene us and the Papiſts: but as it is urged by theſe men, that Chriſts or the Goſpel-Baptiſme, had not the ſame ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, eſpecially in reſpect of the ſame Element of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, with that which they call <hi>Johns</hi> baptiſme, can never be made out by any one argument of theirs; on the other ſide I take it to bee ſufficiently made out already (though it will be more alſo in the exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of particular objections) that the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:117372:36"/>
baptiſme which was by vertue of the Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Commiſſion to continue, as the Preaching of the Word, unto the end of the World, was admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred by water.</p>
            <p>To come now to their arguments, and particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as I finde them layd downe by a nameleſſe Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, who boaſts to have been the firſt that broacht this Doctrine; but if none will contend with him for the glory of this, there are thoſe that will not yeeld an inch to him in things of as great and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable revelation, if to make themſelves God, or calling themſelves the Lord of Hoſts, be things of as great and high a nature as this. This you muſt carry along with you, that the great buſineſſe is to prove that Chriſts baptiſme is not by water: He affirms therefore, as an argument to confirme his premiſes, that <hi>Johns</hi> Baptiſme and Chriſts were diſtinct in their appellations; What will then follow? <hi>Ergo,</hi> Chriſts baptiſme was not adminiſtred by water? Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd, Where lyes the conſequence, or what Logick will inforce it?</p>
            <p>But to goe on, Was not Circumciſion I beſeech you, a leading Ceremony in <hi>Moſes</hi> Law, in as much as all the worſhippers of that Covenant were ſtyled the Circumciſion: it belonged properly and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly, and was the great Ordinance of the <hi>Moſaicall</hi> Law, as you may find, <hi>Acts</hi> 21.21. where the prime inſtance of forſaking <hi>Moſes,</hi> was, not to be circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and that alſo, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.3. <hi>Who ever is circumciſed is a Debtor to doe the whole Law:</hi> This notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Chriſt ſayes, Circumciſion was not of <hi>Moſes,</hi> but of the Fathers. So Baptiſme by water is a lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and principall Ordinance to Chriſtians, as Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:117372:36"/>
was to the Jewes, and yet in the ſame ſenſe may it be ſayd to be not of Chriſt, but of <hi>John,</hi> that is, hee whom it pleaſed God to make uſe of in the firſt adminiſtration of it, was <hi>John.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I beſeech you, is not the Law of the Old Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant as often called <hi>Moſes</hi> Law, as Baptiſme is the Baptiſme of <hi>John,</hi> doth that make <hi>Moſes</hi> therefore the Author or Inſtitutor of that Law, as a thing di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct from the Law of God.</p>
            <p>In like manner, calling Baptiſme by the name of <hi>Johns</hi> baptiſme, doth by no meanes conclude, that it ſhould not be Chriſtian; and Goſpell baptiſme.</p>
            <p>Secondly, our Author alleadgeth, that the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture affirmes that Chriſts baptiſme was to follow <hi>Johns,</hi> not to goe along with it at the ſame time, <hi>I have Baptized you with water, but he ſhall Baptize you,</hi> excellent, therefore Chriſts Baptiſme was not by water, becauſe it was to follow in time; this Logick is as new as his ſo much boaſted of notion.</p>
            <p>In other places, as <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.11. and <hi>Luke</hi> 3.16. <hi>John</hi> ſayth, <hi>I doe Baptize you with water;</hi> In <hi>Marke</hi> yee have it, <hi>I have Baptized you with water, and hee ſhall Baptize you, &amp;c. Mark</hi> 18. It ſeemes here ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parently, that <hi>John</hi> deſcribes the courſe of his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, which was to adminiſter the outward Element, and to give Chriſt his part, which was to doe the ſpirituall worke, therefore when hee ſayes, <hi>hee hath,</hi> he doth not meane that he will doe it no more, and when he ſayes, <hi>hee doth,</hi> it doth not exclude the times paſt, but ſpeakes as I ſay of the proper courſe and parts of his Miniſtry.</p>
            <p>Againe, for that of Chriſt, <hi>Hee ſhall Baptize,</hi> the future is often put for the preſent, parti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ularly in
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:117372:37"/>
the Hebrew Idiom, when perpetuity or continua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is deſigned, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1. <hi>He ſhall bring forth his fruit in his ſeaſon,</hi> Why not here he ſhall baptize, for hee doth baptize; that is, hath this worke or office to baptize with the ſpirit: Beſides, <hi>John</hi> 1.33. yee have it in the Preſent Tenſe affirmed of Chriſt, <hi>This is he that Baptizeth with the holy Ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
               </label> But then it is told us out of <hi>Acts</hi> 1.4, 5. he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them they ſhould waite for the promiſe of the Father, <hi>For John Baptized with water, but yee ſhall be baptized with the holy Ghoſt not many dayes hence,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to what <hi>John</hi> ſayes of himſelfe, <hi>I Baptize you with water, but hee ſhall Baptize you with the holy Ghoſt and with fire:</hi> Therefore <hi>Johns</hi> baptiſme was the baptiſme of water, and Chriſts the baptiſme of the ſpirit, and ſo not one but ſeverall baptiſmes.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> Anſwer, I doe not ſpeake ſtill of the efficacy of baptiſme, but of the Ceremony or Element. It is certaine that here is not a diſtinction of baptiſmes, but of Baptizers, <hi>I Baptize you with water, but he ſhall baptize you with the holy Ghoſt:</hi> Therefore when <hi>John</hi> ſayes, <hi>I Baptize you with water,</hi> hee doth not handle that point, what his baptiſme was, but what hee was himſelfe, to the end that they ſhould not attribute to him that which was proper to Chriſt; for ſo ye have it, <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.11. <hi>Hee that commeth after me is migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier then I, whoſe ſhooes I am not worthy to looſe, he ſhall Baptize with the holy Ghoſt and with fire.</hi> So here yee have what is the vertue of <hi>John,</hi> or of the Miniſter in baptizing, and what of Chriſt: This diſtinction is common to the New Teſtament, and runnes through the whole courſe of the Miniſtry, <hi>I have planted; A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollo watered, but God gave the increaſe:</hi> No Miniſter
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:117372:37"/>
ever gave the holy Ghoſt, ever baptized with the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt and fire, that was Chriſts part: So as when ever baptiſme is adminiſtred, the <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Miniſtry</hi> are to bee diſtinguiſhed. The <hi>Power</hi> is Chriſts, the <hi>Miniſtry Johns,</hi> or any other man qualifyed for it. The baptiſme of the Miniſter is externall, confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring but the ſigne, that of Chriſt internall, conferring the thing ſignifyed: and becauſe <hi>John</hi> who had ſo great an opinion amongſt the Apoſtles, was to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, and our Lord to increaſe, therefore Chriſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances in him, in this place of the firſt of the <hi>Acts,</hi> in oppoſition to his part in the Miniſtry.</p>
            <p>But laſt of all, I aske any man, whether men were not baptized with the holy Ghoſt and with fire, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that time, for firſt the Apoſtles were baptized with the holy Ghoſt before that, the Saints and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers were ſanctifyed, and regenerated, and made holy before then, which is all theſe men would have to be that Ordinance, ſo as things were not annexed and affixed to that famous ſending downe of the holy Ghoſt in the ſhape of fiery tongues, but was before long, during all the courſe of the adminiſtration of baptiſme, though perhaps not with that efficacy and fulneſſe, and glory, as after; for ſo it is true that the holy Ghoſt was not yet given, becauſe Jeſus was not yet gloryfied: So as clearly this place of the <hi>Acts</hi> holds out the excellency and glory of Chriſts admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration, in reſpect of all under-Miniſters, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly in reſpect of <hi>John,</hi> who being the firſt Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of baptiſme, had a peculiar honour from it, and the whole Church here was ſpiritually baptized as in a type; the Apoſtles receiving eminently the holy Ghoſt, not for themſelves but for the Churches.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:117372:38"/>This extraordinary adminiſtration, <hi>Luke</hi> (as <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin</hi> obſerves) improperly, that, is out of the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary ſignification, calls Baptiſme (for baptiſme pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly ſignifies Immerſion) to the end that the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis and oppoſition between Chriſt and <hi>John</hi> might bee intyre; by the ſame reaſon as <hi>Paul</hi> after hee had mentioned the Law of workes, to the end that the Antitheſis might lye on both ſides, faith, <hi>The Law of Faith, Rom.</hi> 3.27.</p>
            <p>After this, wee have a new Interpretation framed upon <hi>Acts</hi> 19. where we are made beleeve that thoſe twelve Diſciples found to be baptized onely by <hi>Johns</hi> baptiſme, were baptized againe in the name of Chriſt, and this baptiſme into the Name of Chriſt, he ſayes was not the repeating of any water, but meerely the gift of the ſpirit: This as the reſt is boldly affirmed, but where lyes his proofe, or how doth hee make it out? It is moſt probable (as it hath beene taken by all to this day) that if this were another baptiſme, or a repetition of baptiſme, it was by water, as well as in ſeverall other places in the <hi>Acts,</hi> where any are ſayd to be baptized, hee himſelfe underſtands it by water, why not as well here? But truely I am of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with thoſe that thinke that <hi>Paul</hi> did not here command any to bee baptized in the Name of the Lord Jeſus, which were already baptized with the baptiſme of <hi>John,</hi> but rather taught that thoſe who had received <hi>Johns</hi> baptiſme were rightly baptized into Chriſt, and therefore had no need of any new, or other baptiſme: It is very probable notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that from this place did either ariſe, or was confirmed in many, the opinion of the difference of theſe two baptiſmes of <hi>John</hi> and Chriſt; though as
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:117372:38"/>
it is now ſtated to us by our nameleſſe Author, hee, for any thing I ſhall ſay to the contrary, ſhall have the honour of the novelty of it.</p>
            <p>But to conſider the place a little particularly, <hi>Paul</hi> being come to <hi>Epheſus</hi> found certaine Diſciples, which afterwards, <hi>Ver.</hi> 7. are ſayd to be about twelve, he preſently askes them if they had received the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt ſince they beleeved? The ſenſe muſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely be (as it will appeare by what followes) have yee received the gifts of the holy Ghoſt, which or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily accompanied faith and baptiſme in thoſe dayes, according to that in the <hi>Acts, Repent and bee Baptized in the Name of the Lord Jeſus</hi> (which our Author will not deny, I ſuppoſe, to bee adminiſtred by water) <hi>and yee ſhall receive the gifts of the holy Ghoſt,</hi> and according to that, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.2. <hi>Received you the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit by the workes of the Law or by the bearing of Faith;</hi> alſo Verſe 5. <hi>He that miniſtreth the ſpirit and worketh miracles among you;</hi> where they are joyned together as things of a kind. Beſides, being Chriſtians, and having beleeved, they could not want the ſpirit of God regenerating, and ſanctifying, for no man can ſay that Jeſus is the Chriſt, but by the ſpirit, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it muſt needs be meant of thoſe extraordinary gifts which were peculiar to thoſe times as an effect of beleeving and baptizing, and yet not common to all.</p>
            <p>They anſwered ſimply, as the thing was, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly to his queſtion, that <hi>they had not ſo much as heard whether there were an holy Ghoſt or no.</hi> The ſenſe whereof muſt cleerly be, that they were ignorant of the holy Ghoſt or knew not whether there were any ſuch thing or no, to wit, as he was then viſible or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:117372:39"/>
to beleevers, in miraculous, and extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry gifts, for elſe being Chriſtians they felt the power of the holy Ghoſt, and being Jewes as they were, they knew that there was a holy Ghoſt by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Scriptures, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. <hi>Lord take not thy holy ſpirit from me;</hi> alſo in the 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 22. <hi>Which way went the ſpirit of the Lord from me to ſpeake to thee;</hi> alſo <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11. <hi>The ſpirit of the Lord was upon him.</hi> So as the ſenſe muſt needs as I have ſayd bee underſtood of the gifts of the ſpirit, <hi>ſcil.</hi> to ſpeake with tongues, prophecy, and the like, for they are ſayd to receive the holy Ghoſt which are adorned with any new or extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary gift.</p>
            <p>Having received an anſwer of this queſtion, hee preſently ſubjoynes another, and askes them, <hi>Ver.</hi> 3. <hi>Unto what then they were baptized?</hi> which follows very pertinently the other, for as he tooke it for granted, that baptiſme immediatly followed beleeving, ſo the adminiſtration of ſpirituall gifts, called receiving the holy Ghoſt, or the gifts of the holy Ghoſt, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily accompanyed baptiſme, ſometimes before it, as a witneſſe they were worthy of baptiſme; as in <hi>Cornelius</hi> and his Family, <hi>Chap.</hi> 10. ſometimes after baptiſme, as to the Apoſtles, yea and our Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe received the holy Ghoſt in the ſhape of a Dove immediately after the receit of baptiſme.</p>
            <p>Having therefore asked them how they were ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiated into Chriſtian Religion; that is, by whom was that ceremony adminiſtred, or how or to what purpoſe were they baptized? They anſwer, that they were baptized into <hi>Johns</hi> baptiſme; which was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per enough, ſignifying that they in baptiſme pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed the Doctrine taught by <hi>John,</hi> ſealed to them
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:117372:39"/>
by the adminiſtration of that Ordinance, but other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe their progreſſe was not great, as having neither heard Chriſt himſelfe, nor his Apoſtles. The like of which was ſayd of Apollo, that <hi>he knew onely the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme of John,</hi> Chap. 18.25. <hi>being inſtructed,</hi> or as <hi>Beza</hi> reads it, <hi>initiated in the way of the Lord,</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing little or nothing more of Chriſt then what <hi>John</hi> preached, and ſealed with his baptiſme.</p>
            <p>So as to be baptized into any ones baptiſme, as in this place, into the baptiſme of <hi>John,</hi> ſignifies to profeſſe, and by the receiving of baptiſme to imbrace the Doctrine which <hi>John</hi> preached and ſealed with that ſigne, the prepoſition <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſignifying the finall cauſe.</p>
            <p>And indeed baptiſme ſeemes to have a threefold ſignification, one proper, which ſignifies immerſion or dipping, which from the effect is alſo called ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, or waſhing: The other two tranſlations, as when it is taken for powring out the gifts of the holy Ghoſt, or when it is taken for the Doctrine which <hi>John</hi> delivered with the ſeale and ceremony ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companying it, as when it is ſayd, that <hi>Apollos</hi> knew nothing but the baptiſme of <hi>John,</hi> for new Doctrines had new Ceremonies accompanying them. After this in the next Verſes, <hi>ſcil.</hi> 4, 5, 6. <hi>Paul</hi> was ſo farre from bidding them to bee baptized in the Name of the Lord Jeſus, that hee taught them rather that thoſe who had received <hi>Johns</hi> baptiſme were duely baptized into Chriſt, and therefore had no need of a new baptiſme, but rather as a conſequence and due of it, might receive the gifts of the holy Ghoſt. For the fourth and fifth Verſes are ſpoken by <hi>Paul,</hi> gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a right account and narrative of the baptiſme
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:117372:40"/>
of <hi>John</hi> with the ground of it, whereas the fourth Verſe, is commonly taken to be ſpoken by <hi>Paul</hi> to thoſe <hi>Epheſians,</hi> but the fifth to bee ſpoken by <hi>Luke,</hi> ſhewing what followed the word of <hi>Paul:</hi> whereas it plainely appeares by the Particles, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which are adverſative, that both thoſe Verſes were ſpoken by <hi>Paul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Verſe 4. <hi>Iohn verely baptized, &amp;c.</hi> Verſe. 5. <hi>But when they heard this, His vero auditis,</hi> ſo as both theſe expreſſions were <hi>Pauls,</hi> teaching that thoſe who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving heard <hi>Iohn</hi> had received baptiſme, were baptiz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into the Name of Chriſt, that is, as before were conſecrated or dedicated by baptiſme unto Chriſt. Then <hi>Verſe</hi> 6. begins the words of <hi>Luke</hi> telling the ſucceſſe of this diſcourſe: <hi>And when Paul had layd his hands on them, &amp;c.</hi> ſignifying that <hi>Paul</hi> did no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe after he had informed them that they were rightly baptized into the Name of Chriſt, then to lay hands on them, upon which followed the gifts of the holy Ghoſt, ſpeaking with tongues, and propheſying.</p>
            <p>So as here is nothing of two baptiſmes, but a right explanation of <hi>Iohns</hi> baptiſme to be the Goſpel bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, or baptiſme into the Name of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
               </label> As for that they object, that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is a tranſitive, and expletive, and a note of tranſition, and ſo <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> exple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> The Anſwer is, That it may bee when <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> precedes not, but when <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> precedes, then no wiſe man will deny it to bee adverſative, and to correct the other part of the narration, as when <hi>Mark</hi> 14. <hi>Truely the Sonne of man goeth as it is written of him: But woe to him by whom the Son of man is betrayed:</hi> No man here will grant that in the firſt place Chriſt ſpeaks, and in the ſecond <hi>Mark.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:117372:40"/>Having thus vindicated the Ordinance of Goſpel-baptiſme from the miſtakes and objections againſt it, I might here make an end, but that the foremention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed nameleſſe Author takes upon him to anſwer the objections brought againſt his novelty, ſeverall of which are certaine men of ſtraw ſet up by himſelfe to be the eaſier by his addreſſes overthrowne. As, that by this meanes we are robbed of our Chriſtendome. Againe, then ſo many ages have erred; alſo, that he is the firſt man that oppoſed it: Then, that Chriſt juſtifies and commands water baptiſme, <hi>Iohn</hi> 3. <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. How that place of <hi>Matthew</hi> which holds out by way of Inſtitution Goſpel baptiſme is to bee under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood; I have formerly ſhewd alſo what a ſympathy &amp; correſpondency there is between the inſtitution and the practice, the one being the Comment upon the other, and therefore ſhall trouble you no further with that which is ſufficiently cleared already, nor not at all with thoſe petty objections I told you of before, which he ſo eaſily formes and anſwers. That argument which hee frames againſt Baptiſme from <hi>Pauls</hi> not being Commiſſioned for it, and thanking God that he had baptized but very few, as <hi>Criſpus</hi> and <hi>Gaius,</hi> and the houſe of <hi>Stephanas,</hi> I have particularly conſidered and anſwered already, when I gave the expoſition of the greateſt part of that Chapter, <hi>ſcil.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. out of which it is rayſed, to which I referre the Reader, not affecting needleſſe repetitions.</p>
            <p>But one objection would trouble him, if he would give it liberty, and let it have its ſcope, and himſelfe ſayes, it ſeemes to be the ſtrongeſt, which is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant practice of the Apoſtles in this c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e not onely before Chriſts baptiſme came in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fter, as he ſays,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:117372:41"/>
as appeares by many places which hee quotes out of the <hi>Acts of the Apoſtles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Objection notwithſtanding doth not much trouble him, for he anſwers it eaſily thus; That the Apoſtles indeed did practice water baptiſme, but not from Chriſt but from <hi>Iohn,</hi> whoſe baptiſme they tooke up, and an outward ceremony of honour and account is not eaſily layd downe. This he helps him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in, and proves by a parallell inſtance, to wit, that ſome of the Apoſtles uſed Circumciſion, and that, after the Aſcenſion of Chriſt, for Circumciſion was an honourable Ceremony uſed from <hi>Abrahams</hi> time, and ſo they could not abruplty lay it downe, but uſed it for their ſakes who were weake: and ſo in like manner the Apoſtles uſed the baptiſme of <hi>Iohn,</hi> or water baptiſme, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Objection that in his account ſeems ſo ſtrong, if he had dealt ingeniouſly he ſhould have beat it out thinner, and conſidered more particularly ſome of thoſe places in the <hi>Acts,</hi> and hee would have found that ſo generall an anſwer would ſcarce have ſerved the turne.</p>
            <p>But I confeſſe in this place as well as in ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers I have much adoe to keepe my ſelfe from que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioning the moralls of theſe men more then their intellectuals. It is true that <hi>Paul</hi> did once uſe a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty in circumciſing one, to wit, <hi>Timothy,</hi> as ye find, <hi>Acts</hi> 16. <hi>Paul</hi> was to viſit the Churches, and having a deſire to take <hi>Timothy</hi> along with him in that work who was wel reported of by the brethren he took and circumciſed him; <hi>Becauſe</hi> (ſaith the Text) <hi>of the Iewes which were in thoſe quarters, for they knew all, that his Father was a Greek:</hi> Leaſt therefore the brethren of
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:117372:41"/>
the Circumciſion ſhould be ſcandalized in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe of a <hi>Gentile,</hi> the breaking downe of the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion wall being yet not ſo manifeſt as was needfull for the ſatisfaction of their ſcrupulous conſciences, <hi>Paul</hi> tooke the advantage of his Mothers being a Jeweſſe, and to avoyd the ſcandal and offence of thoſe brethren, circumciſed him.</p>
            <p>But the ſame <hi>Paul,</hi> who to avoyd the ſcandall of ſome weake brethren, circumciſed <hi>Timothy</hi> (ſuch ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies as Divines uſe to ſay, having then a kind of indifferency in them not being yet honourably bury<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) would by no meanes circumciſe <hi>Titus, Gal.</hi> 2.3. for when there were falſe brethren who might draw that liberty into an ill example, he would not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained by them to circumciſe <hi>Titus,</hi> or hee would not doe that upon any occaſion or ground, which they might prſently reproach him with, as varying from his principles, that he being the great Doctor and Preacher of liberty ſhould yet at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and in the preſence of the Apoſtles, alter his practice.</p>
            <p>And generally where this liberty was knowne and averred, <hi>Paul</hi> was zealous we know to defend it, as we ſee in the caſe of <hi>Peters</hi> eating with the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and withdrawing afterwards, <hi>fearing them of the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, Verſe</hi> 11, 12. and told him, that by his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample he compelled the <hi>Gentiles</hi> to <hi>Judaiſme,</hi> which was intollerable, for even the Jewes by beleeving in Chriſt were delivered from the bondage of ſuch ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, much more the <hi>Gentiles</hi> whoſe portion they never were: You ſee now the force of this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallell in one part of it Circumciſion, let us compare it now with the other of Baptiſme.</p>
            <p>Circumciſion was ſometimes adminiſtred, once
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:117372:42"/>
(as we ſee) and but once that I know by the Apoſtles, after abſolutely refuſed, the reaſon and ground ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, and given for the ſatisfaction of ſome Jewes that were in thoſe quarters, who not having ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient light about thoſe ceremonies would have beene ſcandalized to have ſeene <hi>Paul</hi> taken <hi>Timothy</hi> with him as a companion and fellow-worker uncircumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed; after this, and in another circumſtance, this was abſolutely refuſed as I have ſayd.</p>
            <p>But baptiſme by water adminiſtred frequently by the Apoſtles and Miniſters of the Goſpel, to all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, to all ſorts, <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> who were taught and inſtructed in it, to take it up upon the moſt ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall and Goſpell grounds, to the moſt ſpirituall and Goſpell ends, and that from the beginning of the preaching of the Goſpell to this day, now above ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene hundred years together, without any interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in any age, till the age of this Doctor, who boaſts of a particular felicity in adminiſtring this light to the World.</p>
            <p>Here then I call Heaven and Earth to witneſſe whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther theſe men deale equally and uprightly or no, in the way of their reaſonings and parrallels. To omit other things which will be confeſt by all men, as that not onely <hi>Jewes,</hi> but <hi>Gentiles,</hi> were led into, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in this practice of baptiſme by the Apoſtles, and that after the aſcenſion of Chriſt, when they would have the terme put to this water baptiſme, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven after that, the <hi>Gentiles</hi> received it as a new thing and light from the Apoſtles Circumciſion was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and thoſe that would have Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched it to them were ſayd to <hi>bee troublers and ſubver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of their ſoules, Acts</hi> 15.24. but where ever they
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:117372:42"/>
Preach't Chriſt among the Gentiles, they Preach't alſo this baptiſme either to Jewes or Gentiles, as a Goſpell and New Teſtament Ordinance, which was to continue as long as Preaching, even <hi>to the end of the World, Mat.</hi> 28. So <hi>Peter, Acts</hi> 2. had no ſooner Preach't and converted men, made them Diſciples, but he led them into the Doctrine and Preaching of Baptiſme, <hi>Verſe</hi> 38. <hi>Acts</hi> 8. Thoſe of <hi>Samaria</hi> and the Eunuch had baptiſme preach't and adminiſtred to them as a Goſpell Ordinance, and appendix of Preaching; ſo <hi>Cornelius, Acts</hi> 10. who wayted on <hi>Peter, to heare all things commanded of God, Verſe</hi> 33. was led with his Family into the Doctrine and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of baptiſme by <hi>Peter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the ends of Baptiſme, every one knowes they were the ſame with the Preaching and beleeving of the Goſpell (this being nothing but another way of adminiſtration of the ſame Goſpell) namely, our u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and communion with God in Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But then for the grounds of Baptiſme that they were Goſpell and ſpirituall (if any can be) the whole courſe of the Scripture ſhewes. Is not Faith in the Lord Jeſus, beleeving with all the heart, a ſpirituall and Goſpell ground? Muſt not that needs be a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall and Goſpell Ordinance that hath that for the riſe? But this is the ground and riſe of this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.37. To inſtance but in one place more, is not the receiving of the holy Ghoſt, a ſpiritual and Goſpell ground? Can that Ordinance be legall, and ſervile, and ungoſpell, that hath the baptiſme of the holy Ghoſt, for the riſe and ground of it? Yet ſo it was that this baptiſme by water (which they ſo villy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie as pretending to a Metaphiſicall Religion) after
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:117372:43"/>
the root of their owne carnall and fleſhly wiſedome and not after the fooliſhneſſe of Goſpel adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which yet is wiſedome to thoſe that are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect:) I ſay this baptiſme by water had for its riſe and ground, the powring out of the gifts of the holy Ghoſt: That ſpirituall Baptiſme being an appendix either a due to it when this went before, as <hi>Acts</hi> 2. <hi>Repent and be baptized, and yee ſhall receive the gifts of the holy Ghoſt;</hi> or elſe a ground and riſe of it, as here, the powring out of theſe heavenly gifts giving war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant or title for the adminiſtration of this ordinance.</p>
            <p>But enough to ſhew the vanity and falſhood of theſe men in their argumentations and parrallells, who like Orators that manage an ill cauſe, make leaſt ſtay in the moſt important places.</p>
            <p>And here I ſhould put an end to this diſcourſe of <hi>The Vindication of Goſpell Ordinances,</hi> having ſhown by generall grounds of Scripture, the reaſon of the thing it ſelfe, and a particular inſtance in a leading and prime Ordinance, to wit, baptiſme, that there are cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine formes and inſtitutions remaining with us, ſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and proportioned to our ſtate, which are pledges of Chriſts love to us, tracts and wayes wherein hee delights to meet us, and meanes by which he conveys himſelfe to us in this ſtate of our Pilgrimage, <hi>Whilſt we are at home in the body and abſent from the Lord, whilſt we live by Faith and not by ſight, whilſt wee ſee in a glaſſe darkly, and not face to face, whilſt wee know in part and not as we are knowne.</hi> But leaſt any ſhould thinke that this tends to an undervaluing of the ſpirit of God, or a leſſening of his Empire (though no ſuch thing but the contrary is to be gathered out of all the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes) yet I am not unwilling by way of <hi>Corollary,</hi>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:117372:43"/>
and concluſion to this diſcourſe, to ſpend a few words particularly upon this ſubject; and to profeſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all the World, that nothing ought to be ſo dear to us, and ſo much eſteemed, and ſo much ſought for by us, as the acceſſes and influences of the holy ſpirit: That it is the ſpirit that leads us into all truth, it is the ſpirit that quickens, the ſpirit that comforts us, without which ſince our Lord went into Heaven, we had been left <hi>Orphans and Fatherleſſe:</hi> It is the ſpirit <hi>that ſearcheth all things,</hi> the ſpirit that inables to judge all things, the ſpirit by which wee live, in which wee walke when wee walke with God, and doe any thing that is agreable to his will; it is the ſpirit that ſeales us to the day of redemption, and witneſſeth with our ſpirits, that we are the Sonnes of God.</p>
            <p>It is the ſpirit that hath done all the wonderfull things which the holy Scriptures record; it is the ſpirit that hath given boldneſſe in all ages to doe, and to ſuffer great things, for the Name and Teſtimony of Jeſus: If I ſhould purſue this Theame at large, there would be no end or meane found of the Enco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miums and Elogyes of the ſpirit: It is the fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip therefore and communion of the holy ſpirit which my ſoule breaths after, and longs for, above a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing imaginable. But that which I affirme is, that the ſpirit is communicated to us particularly, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially in ſuch Ordinances as we have been ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of: It was the ſpirit that ſtrove with the old World in the Miniſtry of <hi>Noah</hi> a Preacher of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, and in the adminiſtration of the old Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant the things they were taught and provoked to, were things ſpirituall, and they were ſayd to have <hi>the good ſpirit of the Lord to inſtruct them, Nehem.</hi> 9.10.
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:117372:44"/>
Which was undoubtedly the reaſon, why the Saints of thoſe times breathed ſo much after thoſe Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, which God had fitted to their preſent ſtate and capacity, as things in which the ſpirit inſtructed them, and God bleſt to them, to know more of his mind then all the World by any other way or wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome could doe: For the new and better Covenant under which ſtate and condition we live, the ſpirit is conveyed to us by certaine formes and inſtitutions of Gods owne inventing; Preaching is a great Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance in the hand of God for the conveying of the holy ſpirit, the <hi>Galatians</hi> received the ſpirit by the hearing of Faith preached, <hi>Galat.</hi> 3.3. And we know that generally all the great and famous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſions which are ſeene in the World, by which men are ſayd <hi>to be borne of the ſpirit,</hi> are adminiſtred by the Preaching of the Goſpell in the mouth of the ordinary Miniſters and diſpenſers of it, former times for the greater glory of the beginnings of the Goſpel had greater Harveſts, but the way of adminiſtration was the ſame; then at one Sermon there were added to the Church three thouſand, and whilſt <hi>Peter</hi> was Preaching to <hi>Cornelius</hi> and his friends, <hi>the holy Ghoſt fell upon all them that heard the word,</hi> but the way as I ſayd, is the ſame ever ſince, and <hi>it pleaſes God by the fooliſhneſſe of Preaching to ſave them that beleeve.</hi> And as the holy Ghoſt doth preſide the Miniſtry of prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, ſo the ordinary Officers and Elders of the Church were ſayd to be made <hi>Overſeeers by the holy ghoſt to feed the Church of God which he had purchaſed with his own blood, Acts</hi> 20.28. And for that Ordinance for which wee have more particularly contended, Baptiſme, we are ſayd, <hi>by one ſpirit to bee all baptized
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:117372:44"/>
into one body;</hi> and uſually the adminiſtration of the ſpirit accompanyed baptiſme, either after it as an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendix, or before it as a qualification for that Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, as I have already ſhewed.</p>
            <p>That therefore which makes mee contend for the holy Ordinances of God, and value them to that height, which through the grace of God I do, is that ineſtimable value and eſteeme I put upon the holy ſpirit of God, who is pleaſed to meete us in theſe tracts, and to offer himſelfe to us in theſe admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations.</p>
            <p>But ſuch is the vanity and perverſneſſe of men, that to avoyd errours they runne ever into extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: We ſee it in civill things, thoſe who have found the preſſures of the Tyranny of one man, thinke themſelves never ſafe till they have caſt off all Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and runne willingly into Anarchy, or that which is next to that worſt Democracy, or the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the People. Whereas in all things (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially in things of God and Religion) truth and right is that which lyes in the middle, as diverſe in its owne nature from either extreame, as one extreame is from the other. It were certainely abſurd in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, becauſe it is our ſpirits that immediatly act our bodyes, for us to fall out with our blood, as with a groſſe and dul ſubſtance that we would have nothing to doe with, when as our blood is the <hi>Vehiculum</hi> of our ſpirits: And it is not leſſe abſurd for us in the preſent ſtate wherein we are, to cry out of Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as of things groſſe and diſproportionable to a ſpirituall life and man, when God who knowes our temper better then we our ſelves, uſes them to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey his ſpirit by, and makes them tracts and wayes
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:117372:45"/>
wherein he is wont to meet us. To Idolize and make a God of Ordinances, as if the <hi>opus operatum,</hi> rendred us ſpirituall and agreeable to God, as it hath beene the fault of Chriſtians in many ages, ſo it is the moſt uncomely and moſt unſprituall thing that can be, but for the avoiding of this folly and fault, to fling them all away as things not at all uſefull, becauſe not ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to our carnall reaſonings about ſpirituall things, or capable of an abuſe, is an unſpiritualneſſe and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comelyneſſe no leſſe great then the former. For my part, whilſt God is pleaſed by the fooliſhneſſe of Ordinances to ſave them that beleeve, I ſhall make it my indeavour to be in the poſſeſſion of them, and ſhall expect God in them, for whom onely I deſire them; for others that count themſelves above theſe fooliſh things, it were well for them to learne, that <hi>the fooliſhneſſe of God is wiſer then men,</hi> and it will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly be found their wiſedome (as I ſayd in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning) <hi>to become fooles, that they may be wiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:117372:45"/>
            <head>A Table, directing to ſeverall particulars in the preceding Diſcourſe.</head>
            <list>
               <item>THE Introduction expreſsing the unhappineſſe of theſe times, in reſpect of extravagant opinions in Religion with their tendencie and riſe. <hi>Pa. 1. 2.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The good which God brings out of this evill. <hi>p. 3.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That which immediatly debauches mens ſpirits, is an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dervaluing of Ordinances, and unworthy thoughts of the Scriptures. <hi>p. 4.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Two excellent ends of the Scripture. <hi>p. 5.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>In all matters of Faith and Worſhip, the appeale lyes to the Scripture as to the standard. <hi>p. 6.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Scripture is the rule or ſtandard, notwitſtanding the ignorance or perverſneſſe of Interpreters. <hi>p. 7.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The vanity of affected and myſterious Allegorizing. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The <hi>1</hi> Cor. <hi>3.6. Not of the Letter but of the Spirit,</hi> opened. <hi>p. 8, 9.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Scripture in it ſelfe plaine. <hi>p. 10.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Whom the difficulty eſpeciallly hurts. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Scripture difficulties not relieved by the Allegorizers of theſe times. <hi>p. 11.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>When Allegories may be uſed. <hi>p. 11, 12.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>In what ſenſe naturall men be able to underſtand Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and where they fall ſhort. <hi>p. 13, 14.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>1 Cor. 2.14.</hi> opened. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>VVhat advantage a ſpirituall man hath in interpretation of Scripture, and who he is. <hi>p. 14, 15.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The good intelligence between the Scripture and the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. <hi>p. 16.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The objection of thoſe which thinke the Scriptures have their periods and times with men, beyond which they are not of uſe, conſidered. <hi>p. 17.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:117372:46"/>
                  <hi>1</hi> John <hi>2.20, 21, 27. Yee have an unction, and yee know all things,</hi> opened. <hi>ibid. &amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To know all things, and to know but in part, oppoſed. <hi>p. 18.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>It is no unuſuall Oratory to perſwade men they know al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready what we would further inlighten them in. <hi>p. 19.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The benefit of the new Covenant in oppoſition to the old, wherein it lyes. <hi>p. 22.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2</hi> Pet. <hi>1.19.</hi> Conſidered. <hi>p. 26, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>7, &amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Vindication of the uſe of Ordinances. <hi>p. 30, 31. cum ſequent.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>1</hi> Cor. <hi>1.21.</hi> Conſidered. <hi>p. 31.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>VVhat is knowing Chriſt after the fleſh. <hi>p. 32.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>In what ſenſe <hi>Paul</hi> was ſayd to be <hi>ſent not to Baptize, but to Preach. p. 33, 34.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modating that ſcripture by others parallel to it. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Reaſons why the Ordinances of Inſtitution appeare ſo fooliſh to men unſpirituall. <hi>p. 36.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Men prejudic'd againſt Ordinances, are alſo againſt a Crucified Chriſt. <hi>p. 37.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Col. <hi>2.8. Take heed leaſt any man ſpoyle you through Philoſophie, and vaine deceit,</hi> conſidered. <hi>p. 38.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Men oppoſing Ordinances doe but carnally Philoſophate about ſpirituall things. <hi>p. 38, 39.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Conſiderations why it pleaſed God to ordaine <hi>Mediums</hi> for worſhip, ſo unproportionable to the reaſon and wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of men. <hi>p. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, 40.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the difference betweene Us and the Jewes, who were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Ceremonies, and mediate Ordinances. <hi>p. 41. cum ſequent.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Our ſacraments have the ſame advantage over the Jewes Sacraments, that the Goſpell hath over the Law. <hi>p. 42.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Many after they have ſerved their turne of Chriſt Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
<pb facs="tcp:117372:46"/>
fling him away, as an element as beggarly as thoſe Ordinances they cry downe. <hi>p. 43.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The ſame reaſon of Preaching or conference in reſpect of ſpiritualneſſe with Baptiſme, or the Table of the Lord. <hi>p. 44, 45.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The vanity of ſuch as would lay aſide Ordinances, becauſe outward and carnall, manifeſted by the conſideration of our way of holding com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God in this life and ſtate. <hi>p. 46, 47.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The true notion of the Word <hi>Spirituall,</hi> in order to the diſcourſe in hand. <hi>p. 47, 48, 49, 50.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Never way of Worſhip was chang'd without a great noteriety to thoſe whom it concerned. <hi>p. 50, 51, 52, 53, 54.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Ordinance of Baptiſme vindicated, being an illuſtrious inſtance for the abiding and continuing with us, of other Inſtitutions. <hi>p. 55. cum ſequent.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The ſtate of the controverſie as it lyes between us and the Papiſts, and between us and the men we contend againſt. <hi>p. 55, 56, 57.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The new expoſition of Mat. <hi>28.19, 20. Go teach all Natione, Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing them, &amp;c.</hi> ſhewed to be bold and abſurd. <hi>p. 59, 60, 61.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Inſtitution of Baptiſme, <hi>Mat. 28.</hi> and Apoſtolicall practice which is the beſt comment upon the rule, exactly agreeing. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Severall arguments of theſe new men againſt Baptiſme by water, exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined. <hi>p. 62. cum ſequent.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Johns</hi> Baptiſme and Chriſts was diſtinct in their appellations, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered. <hi>p. 62</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chriſts Baptiſme was to follow <hi>Johns,</hi> conſidered. <hi>p. 63.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>John <hi>Baptized with water, but ye ſhall be Baptized with the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt,</hi> conſidered. <hi>p. 64, 65.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Objection againſt baptiſme out of <hi>Acts 19.</hi> conſidered. <hi>p. 66, 67, 68, 69.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Receiving the holy Ghoſt, ordinarily accompanyed Baptiſme, either be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore or after it. <hi>p. 68.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Three ſeverall ſignifications of Baptiſme. <hi>p. 69.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A weighty argument for Baptiſme, the conſtant practice of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, very eaſily ſleighted by theſe Novellers, how ingenuouſly let the Reader judge. <hi>p. 71, 72.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The forementioned Argument with the Anſwers of theſe men particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly urged and examined. <hi>p. 72, 73, 74, 75, 76.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Baptiſme by Water adminiſtred conſtantly by the Apoſtles and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Goſpel to all ſorts, upon the moſt ſpirituall grounds, to
<pb facs="tcp:117372:47"/>
the moſt ſpirituall ends. <hi>p. 74, 75, 76.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Contending for Ordinances, no undervaluing the ſpirit, or leſſening his Empire. <hi>p. 76.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Nothing ought to be ſo deare, and ſo much ſought for as the acceſſes of the ſpirit. <hi>p. 77.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Encomiums of the ſpirit in reſpect of its wonderfull Operations. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The holy ſpirit is communicated particularly and eſpecially in the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances. <hi>p. 77, 78, 79.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Men uſually to avoyd errours, run into extremities, as is to be ſeene in other things, as well as in the matter of Ordinances. <hi>p. 79.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Some of the faults eſcaped in the Printing, the Reader is deſired to mend, as followeth.</head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>Page.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>Line.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>Error.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>Correct.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2.</cell>
                     <cell>25.</cell>
                     <cell>After the word <hi>jergona</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Comma.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>4.</cell>
                     <cell>8.</cell>
                     <cell>The word <hi>Secondly</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>to be left out.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>7.</cell>
                     <cell>2.</cell>
                     <cell>For <hi>ſandard,</hi> read</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ſtandard.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>14.</cell>
                     <cell>14.</cell>
                     <cell cols="2">put out the Comma after <hi>transforme,</hi> and add it after <hi>beholding.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>18.</cell>
                     <cell>2.</cell>
                     <cell cols="2">make a Comma after the word <hi>without,</hi> and put out that which followes the word <hi>Word.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>21.</cell>
                     <cell>3.</cell>
                     <cell>for <hi>into,</hi> read</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>in.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>23.</cell>
                     <cell>16.</cell>
                     <cell>for <hi>extream neceſſaries,</hi> read</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>extreamely neceſſary.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>27.</cell>
                     <cell>8.</cell>
                     <cell>for <hi>his,</hi> read</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>its.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>41.</cell>
                     <cell>26.</cell>
                     <cell>after the word <hi>as,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>add the word <hi>there.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>43.</cell>
                     <cell>3.</cell>
                     <cell cols="2">blot out the Comma after the word <hi>efficacy.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>45.</cell>
                     <cell>laſt.</cell>
                     <cell>in ſtead of <hi>&amp;c.</hi> read</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>and.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>49.</cell>
                     <cell>12.</cell>
                     <cell>after the word <hi>of,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>put a <hi>Comma.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>79.</cell>
                     <cell>2.</cell>
                     <cell>for <hi>occompanyed,</hi> read</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>accompanied.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Reader is alſo deſired to minde, that by reaſon of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors diſtance, amongſt other miſtakes, there is one in the running Title: It ſhould have beene,</hi> A Vindication of the uſe of Scriptures; &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
